蒂姆·罗宾斯
摩根·弗里曼
肖申克的救赎
杜弗瑞恩先生
Mr. Dufresne, describe...
请描述一下你妻子遇害当晚你们吵架时的情况
the confrontation you had with your wife the night she was murdered.
我非常痛苦
It was very bitter.
她说被我发现反倒轻松多了 再也不用成天提心吊胆的了
She said she was glad I knew, that she hated all the sneaking around.
美国著名的"离婚城市" 凡欲离婚者 在该市住满三个月即可获准离婚
她还说她要去里诺市和我离婚
And she said that she wanted a divorce in Reno.
- 你当时是如何回答她的? - 我告诉她我不会同意
- What was your response? - I told her I would not grant one.
"我怕你活不到在里诺市见我的那天了!"
"I'll see you in hell before I see you in Reno."
据你邻居的证词 杜弗瑞恩先生 这是你当时的回答
Those were your words, according to your neighbors.
也许吧
If they say so.
我的确不记得了 当时完全气昏头了
I really don't remember. I was upset.
你们吵完架之后发生了什么事?
What happened after you argued with your wife?
她收拾了一包东西
She packed a bag.
她收了包东西 搬到昆汀先生那儿去住了
She packed a bag to go and stay with Mr. Quentin.
格伦·昆汀 斯诺登俱乐部高尔夫教练
Glenn Quentin, golf pro at the Snowden Hills Country Club...
其被你发现与你妻子偷情
whom you had discovered was your wife's lover.
你有没有尾随她?
Did you follow her?
我先是去的酒吧
I went to a few bars first.
之后 我开车去昆汀家找他们 但他们不在
Later, I drove to his house to confront them. They weren't home.
我把车停在路岔口
I parked in the turnout...
在车里等
and waited.
当时你有什么企图?
With what intention?
我自己到现在也说不清
I'm not sure.
当时我心里很乱
I was confused...
又喝了不少酒
drunk.
我想
I think...
顶多也就是想吓吓他们而已
mostly I wanted to scare them.
他们回来后 你就进屋杀了他们
When they arrived, you went up to the house and murdered them.
没有 我开始清醒过来
No.I was sobering up.
回到车子里 然后开车回家 想着睡一觉会好过一些
I got back in the car and I drove home to sleep it off.
半路上 我停车把枪扔进了Royal河里
Along the way, I threw my gun into the Royal River.
这一点我记得很清楚
I've been very clear on this point.
离奇的是次日一早清洁女佣发现
I get hazy where the cleaning woman shows up the following morning...
你妻子和她的情人在床上
and finds your wife in bed with her lover...
被点三八口径的子弹打得如同马蜂窝一般
riddled with.38-caliber bullets.
你不觉得这种巧合来得太蹊跷了吗? 还是只有我这么认为
Does that strike you as a fantastic coincidence, or is it just me?
的确很蹊跷
Yes, it does.
然而你仍旧坚持在凶案发生前
Yet you still maintain you threw your gun into the river...
你已经把枪扔进河里
before the murders took place.
这个说法倒是很省事
That's very convenient.
这是事实
It's the truth.
警方花三天时间摸遍了整条河道 并没找到一把枪
The police dragged that river for three days, and nary a gun was found...
因此也就无法鉴定命中受害者的那些子弹
so no comparison could be made between your gun and the bullets...
是否与你那把枪的弹道相吻合
taken from the bloodstained corpses of the victims.
这对你来说同样非常省事
And that also...
不是吗 杜弗瑞恩先生?
is very convenient. Isn't it, Mr. Dufresne?
恰恰因为我是无辜的 先生
Since I am innocent of this crime...
所以找不到枪反倒对我非常麻烦
I find it decidedly inconvenient that the gun was never found.
诸位陪审员 你们听到了所有的证据
Ladies and gentlemen, you've heard all the evidence.
被告曾到过凶案现场 并留下脚印
We have the accused at the scene of the crime. We have footprints.
散落在现场的子弹上有被告的指纹
Bullets on the ground bearing his fingerprints.
还有一只打碎的酒瓶 同样有他的指纹
A broken bourbon bottle, likewise with fingerprints.
最重要的是
And most of all...
一位漂亮的年轻妇人和她的情人
we have a beautiful young woman and her lover...
双双死在对方的怀抱中
lying dead in each other's arms.
他们是有过错
They had sinned.
但他们的过错是否严重到
But was their crime so great...
需要付出生命作为代价呢?
as to merit a death sentence?
在你们作出结论之前
While you think about that...
请先看看这个
think about this:
一只左轮手枪只能填装六颗子弹 而不是八颗
A revolver holds six bullets, not eight.
所以我认定这不是一时冲动才犯下的罪行
I submit that this was not a hot-blooded crime of passion.
即使那不能被宽恕 至少还可以理解
That at least could be understood, if not condoned.
不是!
No.
这是一次复仇行为
This was revenge...
出于一种特别残忍 冷血的本性
of a much more brutal, cold-blooded nature. Consider this:
想想看 每个受害人身中四枪
Four bullets per victim.
总共开了八枪 而不是六枪
Not six shots fired, but eight.
那表明他打完一轮子弹后
That means that he fired the gun empty...
曾停下来填装子弹
and then stopped to reload...
然后继续向受害人开枪
so that he could shoot each of them again.
每人补射一枪
An extra bullet per lover...
正中头部!
right in the head.
杜弗瑞恩先生 你的冷酷无情 不知悔改让人震惊
You strike me as a particularly icy and remorseless man, Mr. Dufresne.
看到你都令我心寒齿冷
It chills my blood just to look at you.
依据缅因州赋予我的权利
By the power vested in me by the state of Maine...
我判处你连服两项终身监禁
I hereby order you to serve two life sentences back-to-back...
分别告慰两位受害人 退庭!
one for each of your victims. So be it!
坐!
Sit.
你因被判终身监禁己在此服刑二十年?
We see you've served 20 years of a life sentence?
- 是的 先生 - 你认为你已经改过自新了吗?
- Yes, sir. - You feel you've been rehabilitated?
是的 先生 绝对改了 先生
Yes, sir. Absolutely, sir.
我是说 我已经接受教训了
I mean, I learned my lesson.
说实话我已经完全改变了
I can honestly say that I'm a changed man.
我不再对社会有威胁了
I'm no longer a danger to society.
我可以向上帝保证
That's God's honest truth.
驳回
嗨 瑞德
Hey, Red.
怎么样啊?
How'd it go?
还能怎么样? 日子不同罢了
Same old shit, different day.
我知道你心里什么滋味
Yeah, I know how you feel.
下周轮到我要去申请"驳回"了
I'm up for rejection next week.
是啊 我是上周被"驳回"的
Yeah, I got rejected last week.
一向如此
It happens.
嗨 瑞德 借我一包烟
Hey, Red, bump me a deck.
离我远点伙计! 你都欠我五包烟了
Get out of my face, man! You're into me for five packs already.
- 四包! - 五包!
Four!
美国的每座监狱里大概都有像我一样的人物
There must be a con like me in every prison in America.
我就是能够给你搞进来东西的那个人
I'm the guy who can get it for you.
香烟 大麻 只要你喜欢
Cigarettes, a bag of reefer, if that's your thing...
或者孩子高中毕业 你想来瓶白兰地高兴一下
bottle of brandy to celebrate your kid's high school graduation.
几乎任何合理的需求
Damn near anything within reason.
美国著名连锁公司 以百货零售著称
信不信由你 我差不多就是这里正规经营的 西尔斯&罗巴克
Yes, sir! I'm a regular Sears and Roebuck.
所以当安迪·杜弗瑞恩1949年来找我
So when Andy Dufresne came to me in 1949...
1940年代好莱坞著名女星 以性感著称
让我替他搞张 丽塔·海华斯的海报进来时
and asked me to smuggle Rita Hayworth into the prison for him...
我跟他说 "没问题"
I told him, "No problem."
安迪是1947年开春时节被送到肖申克监狱的
Andy came to Shawshank Prison...
罪名是谋杀他的妻子和她的小白脸
in early 1947 for murdering his wife and the fella she was banging.
入狱以前 他是波特兰银行的副总裁
On the outside, he'd been vice president of a large Portland bank.
年青有为
Good work for a man so young.
你会说英语吗 肥牛?
You speak English, butt-steak?
跟这个长官走
You follow this officer.
我这辈子还没见过一堆长这么烂的杂碎
I never seen such a sorry-Iooking heap of maggot shit in all my life.
嗨菜鸟! 到这儿来!
Hey, fish! Come over here!
今天要赌吗 瑞德?
Taking bets today, Red?
赌烟还是赌钱? 自己选
Smokes or coin? Bettor's choice.
香烟 我赌两根
Smokes. Put me down for two.
好吧 你押哪匹马?
All right, who's your horse?
又矮又瘦那个
That little sack of shit.
- 第八个 排第八那个 我赌他最快 - 不可能! 我和你赌! 你输定了
- Eighth. He'll be first. - Bullshit! I'll take that action.
海伍德 就你机灵 那你押啊
If you're so smart, you call it.
我押那个大屁股
I'll take that chubby fat-ass there.
排在第五的那个 五根香烟
The fifth one. Put me down for a quarter deck.
菜鸟上市啦!
Fresh fish today!
又有操练的啦!
We're reeling them in!
我得承认第一眼看到安迪的时候并没觉得他有什么特别
I admit I didn't think much of Andy first time I laid eyes on him.
他看上去弱不胜衣 仿佛一阵风就能吹跑
Looked like a stiff breeze would blow him over.
这是我对他的第一印象
That was my first impression of the man.
你押哪个?
What do you say?
那个大个子 一身富贵子弟打扮那个
That tall drink of water with the silver spoon up his ass.
那家伙? 不可能!
That guy? Never happen.
- 我赌十根香烟! - 那可是笔大买卖!
- 10 cigarettes. - That's a rich bet.
都有谁想来赢我?
Who's going to prove me wrong?
海伍德? 济格?
Heywood? Jigger?
斯基兹?
Skeets?
弗洛伊德?
Floyd!
四个猛男
Four brave souls.
马上返回本人牢房 准备点名!
Return to your cellblocks for evening count.
所有人犯马上返回自己牢房!
All prisoners, return to your cellblocks.
向右转!
Turn to the right!
向前看!
Eyes front.
这位是哈德利先生 他是看守长
This is Mr. Hadley. He's captain of the guards.
我是诺顿先生 典狱长
I'm Mr. Norton, the warden.
你们都是被判有罪的恶棍
You are convicted felons.
因此被送到我这里来
That's why they've sent you to me.
规则一
Rule number one:
不得亵渎神明!
No blasphemy.
在我的监狱里不准许对主的名字不敬
I'll not have the Lord's name taken in vain in my prison.
其它规则
The other rules...
你们慢慢就会知道了 有问题吗?
you'll figure out as you go along. Any questions?
我们什么时候吃饭?
When do we eat?
我们叫你吃你就吃
You eat when we say you eat.
我们叫你拉你就拉 我们叫你尿你就尿
You shit when we say you shit, and piss when we say you piss.
听懂没有? 你个狗娘养的烂人!
You got that, you maggot-dick motherfucker?
站好!
On your feet.
我相信两样东西
I believe in two things:
惩戒 以及经书
Discipline and the Bible.
在这里 你们都会得到
Here, you'll receive both.
把你们的信仰托付给上帝
Put your trust in the Lord.
你们的臭皮囊交由我差遣
Your ass belongs to me.
欢迎来到肖申克
Welcome to Shawshank.
解开锁链
Unhook them.
转身
Turn around.
行了
That's enough.
往外来点
Move to the end of the cage.
转身 撒除虱粉 (消毒粉)
Turn around. Delouse him.
转身
Turn around.
出来 去领你的衣服和圣经
Move out of the cage. Pick up your clothes and Bible.
下一个!
Next man up!
往右走
To the right.
右边 右边
Right. Right.
左边
Left.
不用问 入狱的第一夜是最难熬的
The first night's the toughest. No doubt about it.
像刚出生那天一样光着屁股 被他们驱赶前行
They march you in naked as the day you were born...
除虱粉蜇得你浑身火烧火燎地痛 眼睛几乎半瞎
skin burning and half-blind from that delousing shit.
当他们把你丢进牢房 砰地关上铁栅栏
And when they put you in that cell...and those bars slam home...
那时你才真的回过神儿来 这是玩儿真的!
that's when you know it's for real.
眨眼间过去的生活便离你远去
Old life blown away in the blink of an eye.
什么都没留下 却留给你大把的时间去想念过去
Nothing left but all the time in the world to think about it.
大部分新来的犯人在第一晚都近乎要发疯
Most new fish come close to madness the first night.
总会有人绷不住 痛哭流涕
Somebody always breaks down crying.
一贯如此
Happens every time.
我们关心的问题是
The only question is...
谁是这第一个哭出来的人?
who's it going to be?
这是一个可以拿来打赌的绝佳问题
It's as good a thing to bet on as any, I guess.
我把赌注押在安迪·杜弗瑞恩身上
I had my money on Andy Dufresne.
熄灯
Lights out!
我还记得我在这里的第一夜
I remember my first night.
那似乎已经是很久以前的事了
Seems like a long time ago.
嗨 菜鸟
Hey, fish.
菜鸟 菜鸟 菜鸟 菜鸟～
Fish, fish.
你干嘛呢? 怕黑了吗?
What are you, scared of the dark?
我打赌 你恨不得你老爸从没叉过你老妈
Bet you wish your daddy never dicked your mama!
小猪猪! 小肉肉! 真想要你给我爽一下
Piggy! Pork! I want me a pork chop.
他们总是要戏弄刚入狱的人
The boys always go fishing with first-timers.
不逗哭一个不算完
And they don't quit till they reel someone in.
嗨 大屁股
Hey, Fat Ass.
大屁股!
Fat Ass!
和我说说话吧小子
Talk to me, boy.
我知道你在哪儿 我都听见你喘气儿了
I know you're there. I can hear you breathing.
别听那些傻B瞎掰 你听到没有?
Don't you listen to these nitwits, you hear me?
这地方没那么差
This place ain't so bad.
告诉你为什么
Tell you what...
我可以带你四处走走 让你感觉就像在家一样
I'll introduce you around, make you feel right at home.
我认识一对壮得像牛一样的同志哥
I know a couple of big old bull queers that'd just...
他们一定很乐意跟你混个脸熟
Iove to make your acquaintance.
还有你那又白又嫩的大屁股
Especially that big, white, mushy butt of yours.
噢上帝!
God!
我不该在这里
I don't belong here!
- 嗨 有人胜出了 - 我要回家
- We have a winner! - I want to go home!
大屁股率先撞线
And it's Fat Ass by a nose!
小菜鸟! 小菜鸟!
Fresh fish!
我要回家!
I want to go home!
我要见我妈妈
I want my mother!
我干过你妈妈啦! 她没那么好啦!
I had your mother! She wasn't that great!
又他妈在臭屁什么基督的话?
What the Christ is this horseshit?
你亵渎神明 我要向典狱长告发
He blasphemed. I'll tell the warden.
等我用警棍叉烂你的屁眼你再去告吧
You'll tell him with my baton up your ass!
放我出去
Let me out!
你他妈个饭桶样 想搞什么飞机?
What is your malfunction, you fat barrel of monkey spunk?
求您了! 我没想过会被关起来
Please! I ain't supposed to be here.
不是我干的
Not me!
我可没心情数到三 连一我都不数
I won't count to three. Not even to one.
你马上闭嘴 不然我给你来段摇篮曲!
You shut up, or I'll sing you a lullaby!
- 别说了 呆子 - 求您了 这件事弄错了
Shut up, man. Shut up!
您不了解 我不知道会被送到这儿来
You don't understand. I'm not supposed to be here.
把门打开
Open that cell.
我也是! 这里被他们弄得就像他妈的监狱
Me neither! They run this place like a fucking prison!
你个婊子养的
Son of a bitch!
长官 算了
Captain, take it easy!
如果今晚让我听到还有谁敢在这儿放个屁
If I hear so much as a mouse fart in here tonight...
我向上帝和耶稣发誓 叫你们吃不了兜着走
I swear by God and Jesus, you will all visit the infirmary.
你们这些狗杂种一个都别想溜
Every last motherfucker in here.
叫值班的过来 把这坨臭大粪弄到医务室去
Call the trustees. Take that tub of shit down to the infirmary.
杜弗瑞恩的第一晚 让我输了两包烟
His first night in the joint, Dufresne cost me two packs of cigarettes.
整个晚上他都一声不响
He never made a sound.
北仓三楼 到齐
Tier 3 north, clear count!
北仓二楼 到齐
Tier 2 north, clear count.
南仓三楼 到齐
Tier 3 south, clear.
转向楼梯!
Prepare to roll out.
齐步走!
Roll out!
那东西你吃不吃?
Are you going to eat that?
不 我还没想过
I hadn't planned on it.
能给我吗?
Do you mind?
啊! 白白胖胖的
That's nice and ripe.
杰克说谢谢你
Jake says thank you.
它从制板车间上面的窝里掉下来
Fell out of his nest over by the plate shop.
我得照顾它长大到会飞为止
I'm going to look after him until he's big enough to fly.
哦妈的! 那家伙过来了
Oh, no! Here he comes.
早啊 伙计们
Morning, fellas.
今天天气真好 不是吗?
Fine morning, isn't it?
你们都明白天气为什么这么好 对吗?
You know why it's a fine morning, don't you?
都给我拿过来 我来给它们排排队
Send them down. I want them lined up...
排个漂亮的小仪仗队型
just like a pretty little chorus line.
看看这个
Look at that.
真受不了这鸟人
- I can't stand this guy. - Oh, Lord!
美国著名烟草产地
这就对了 弗吉尼亚 里士满
Yes! Richmond, Virginia.
吃我的屁吧你
Smell my ass!
再吃我的
After he smells mine.
瑞德 我有点替你脸红啊 你的马儿真不给你长脸
That's a shame about your horse coming in last and all.
不过我可爱死我那匹马儿了
But I sure do love that winning horse of mine, though.
等见了他一定得结结实实地亲他一口
I owe that boy a big kiss when I see him.
你干嘛不分几根烟给他? 走运的龟孙子!
Why don't you give him some of your cigarettes instead? Lucky fuck!
嗨 泰利奥!
Hey, Tyrell.
这周是你在医务室值班吧?
You pull infirmary duty this week?
我那匹马儿怎么样了?
How's my horse doing anyway?
死了!
Dead.
哈德利把他的脑袋打开了花
Hadley busted his head up pretty good.
晚上医生都回家了
Doc had gone home for the night.
可怜的家伙就那么躺到天亮
Poor bastard lay there till this morning.
到那会儿怎么救都晚了
By then, there wasn't nothing we could do.
他叫什么名字?
What was his name?
你说什么?
What'd you say?
我只是想问有人知道他的名字吗?
I was just wondering if anyone knew his name.
关他妈你什么屁事 新来的?
What the fuck do you care, new fish?
别他妈打听他的名字了 他死了
Doesn't fucking matter what his name was. He's dead.
嗨 有人找过你吗?
Anybody come at you yet?
有人搞过你吗?
Anybody get to you yet?
嗨 在这里我们都需要朋友
Hey, we all need friends in here.
我可以做你的朋友
I could be a friend to you.
不好上手啊
Hard to get.
我喜欢
I like that.
最初那段时间的安迪一直沉默寡言
Andy kept pretty much to himself at first.
也许他心里有很多想法
I guess he had a lot on his mind...
在努力适应大牢里的生活
trying to adapt to life on the inside.
他是一个月之后才开口
Wasn't until a month went by before he opened his mouth...
和一个人一次说话超过两句以上的
to say more than two words to somebody.
实不相瞒
As it turned out...
那个人就是我
that somebody was me.
我是安迪·杜弗瑞恩
I'm Andy Dufresne.
杀妻银行家
Wife-killing banker.
你为什么杀她?
Why'd you do it?
不是我杀的 既然你有此一问
I didn't, since you ask.
那你算来对地方了
You're going to fit right in.
这儿的每个人都是无辜的 你还不知道吧?
Everybody in here's innocent. Didn't you know that?
海伍德 你怎么进来的? 什么都没做 我被律师设计了
- What you in here for? - Didn't do it. Lawyer fucked me.
传说你很拽啊
Rumor has it you're a real cold fish.
你觉得自己尿得比别人高一点儿 是吗?
You think your shit smells sweeter than most. Is that right?
你看呢?
What do you think?
说实话 我还不知道
To tell you the truth, I haven't made up my mind.
我知道你有办法弄东西进来
I understand you're a man that knows how to get things.
这事儿大家一向都知道
I'm known to locate certain things from time to time.
不知道你能不能帮我弄个鹤嘴槌进来? 什么?
I wonder if you might get me a rock hammer.
鹤嘴槌!
A rock hammer.
- 那是什么东西? 你要来干嘛? - 你担心什么?
- What is it and why? - What do you care?
那要是把牙刷我也懒得问你 直接给你开价
For a toothbrush, I wouldn't ask. I'd quote a price.
因为牙刷伤不了人 听懂没有?
But a toothbrush is a non-lethal object, isn't it?
我明白了
Fair enough.
鹤嘴槌大概长六到七英寸的样子
A rock hammer is about six or seven inches long.
- 看起来像个小号的镐头 - 镐头?
- Looks like a miniature pickax. - Pickax?
- 敲石头用的 - 石头?
For rocks.
石英石吗?
Quartz?
石英
Quartz.
还有云母 页岩
And some mica, shale...
石灰石
limestone.
就这些?
So?
是的 我喜欢玩儿石头
So I'm a rock hound.
曾经玩儿过一段时间 现在想重新捡起来
At least I was in my old life. I'd like to be again.
你别是想用你的玩具敲谁的脑袋吧
Or maybe you'd like to sink your toy into somebody's skull.
不会 我在这里没有仇人
No, I have no enemies here.
没有? 你先等等
No? Wait a while.
话都传开了
Word gets around.
姐妹们特喜欢你
The Sisters have taken quite a liking to you.
尤其是伯格斯
Especially Bogs.
跟他们说我不是同性恋也没用吗?
Don't suppose it would help if I told them I'm not homosexual.
他们也不是
Neither are they.
同性恋怎么说也是人 这几个是畜牲
You have to be human first. They don't qualify.
霸王可以硬上弓 他们就知道这个
Bull queers take by force. That's all they want or understand.
我要是你 得在后脑勺再安双眼睛
If I were you, I'd grow eyes in the back of my head.
- 谢谢你的提醒 - 不客气 这个不收费
- Thanks for the advice. - Well, that's free.
你知道我的顾虑了吧?
You understand my concern.
要是我有麻烦也不用鹤嘴槌 行了吧?
If there's trouble, I won't use the rock hammer.
那么你八成是想越狱 在墙根挖条地道什么的?
Then I'd guess you want to escape. Tunnel under the wall, maybe.
我说错了么? 你笑什么?
What did I miss? What's so funny?
等看见鹤嘴槌你就明白了
You'll understand when you see the rock hammer.
买这个东西一般要多少钱?
What's an item like this usually go for?
七美元 随便一家石器店都买得到
Seven dollars in any rock-and-gem shop.
我一般抽两成
My normal markup's 20 percent.
但这东西情况特别
But this is a specialty item.
风险增加 价钱也得增加 一口价 10元
Risk goes up, price goes up. Let's make it an even 10 bucks.
那就10元吧
Ten it is.
依我看你那是白花钱
Waste of money, if you ask me.
为什么?
Why's that?
这儿的条子喜欢搞突击检查
Folks around this joint love surprise inspections.
被他们发现 你这东西就保不住了
They find it, you're going to lose it.
要是真被他们发现 你可别把我卖了
If they catch you, you don't know me.
你要是把我扯出来 今后就不用来找我拿东西了
Mention my name, we never do business again.
哪怕一副鞋带一根口香糖都别想 记住没有?
Not for shoelaces or a stick of gum. Now you got that?
放心好了
I understand.
谢谢你 你叫...
Thank you, Mr...
瑞德
Red.
叫我瑞德就行
Name's Red.
这名字怎么来的?
Why do they call you that?
可能因为我是爱尔兰人吧
Maybe it's because I'm Irish.
我现在明白为什么有人说他是个异类了
I could see why some of the boys took him for snobby.
他有股子气定神闲的劲儿
He had a quiet way about him...
一言一行都跟周围人不一样
a walk and a talk that just wasn't normal around here.
他信步走去
He strolled...
就像是一名在公园里散步的男子 了无羁绊
like a man in the park without a care or a worry in the world.
仿佛穿了件无形的外套 把他和这个地方隔绝开来
Like he had on an invisible coat that would shield him from this place.
说句良心话
I think it'd be fair to say...
第一次接触我就对安迪产生了好感
I liked Andy from the start.
快点! 有人得抓点紧了
Let's go! Some of us got a schedule to keep.
动起来 快点 动起来
Move it! Come on, move it!
最近还好吧? 你老婆对你怎么样?
How you doing? How's the wife treating you?
瑞德!
Red!
安迪说中了
Andy was right.
我最终明白他为什么发笑了
I finally got the joke.
估计要花六百年
It would take a man about 600 years...
才能用这东西在墙根挖出一条地道
to tunnel under the wall with one of these.
- 要书吗? - 今天不要
- Book? - Not today.
要书吗?
Book?
交给杜弗瑞恩
Delivery for Dufresne.
杜弗瑞恩 这是你的书
Here's your book.
谢谢
Thanks.
杜弗瑞恩 漂白粉快用完了 你去后面拿点来
We're running low on hexite. Get on back and fetch us up some.
这东西会弄瞎你的眼睛
This will blind you.
亲爱的 别紧张
Honey, hush.
这就对了 你越反抗
That's it. You fight!
我感觉越刺激
Better that way.
我很想告诉你 安迪打得很漂亮
I wish I could tell you Andy fought the good fight...
姐妹们没能把他怎么样
and the Sisters let him be.
我希望我可以这么告诉你
I wish I could tell you that...
但是监狱不是童话世界
but prison is no fairy-tale world.
他从没说过是谁干的
He never said who did it.
但我们都明白是怎么回事
But we all knew.
日子就这样一天天过去
Things went on like that for a while.
监狱生活就像例行公事
Prison life consists of routine...
除此之外还是例行公事
and then more routine.
安迪脸上不断出现新的伤痕
Every so often, Andy would show up with fresh bruises.
姐妹们不断侵犯他
The Sisters kept at him.
有时他能逃脱
Sometimes he was able to fight them off.
有时不能
Sometimes not.
这就是安迪的监狱生活
And that's how it went for Andy.
这就是他的例行公事
That was his routine.
我相信最初那两年是他最糟糕的两年
I do believe those first two years were the worst for him.
我也相信如果日子继续这样过下去的话
And I also believe that if things had gone on that way...
这个地方早晚会把他给毁了
this place would have got the best of him.
但是 在1949年的春天
But then, in the spring of 1949...
监狱管理层决定
the powers that be decided:
制板车间的屋顶需要修整
The roof of the license-plate factory needs resurfacing.
我需要12名志愿者工作一周
I need a dozen volunteers for a week's work.
你们都知道
As you know...
特殊的任务意味着特殊的待遇
special detail carries with it special privileges.
这是一次户外劳务
It was outdoor detail...
而五月份是户外劳务的最他妈好的时间了
and May is one damned fine month to be working outdoors.
排好队
Stay in line there.
有一百多人报名参加志愿劳务
More than a hundred men volunteered for the job.
威勒斯·E·安戈
Wallace E. Unger.
艾力斯·瑞丁（瑞德的大名）
Ellis Redding.
你看出来了吧?
Wouldn't you know it?
我和我的朋友们都被选中了
Me and some fellows I know were among the names called.
安迪·杜弗瑞恩
Andrew Dufresne.
这只花了我们每人一包烟的代价
It only cost us a pack of smokes per man.
我当然还是照例抽两成
I made my usual 20 percent, of course.
那牛B律师从德州打长途给我
So this big-shot lawyer calls me long-distance from Texas.
我说 "什么事? "
I say, "Yeah?"
他说 "很抱歉通知你 你哥哥刚刚过世"
He says, " Sorry to inform you, but your brother just died."
这真让人难过
- I'm sorry to hear that. - I'm not. He was an asshole.
我可不难过 那混蛋死就死了 跑那么多年 早当他死了
Ran off years ago. Figured him for dead.
那律师对我说"他死的时候非常富有"
So this lawyer fellow says to me:
什么狗屁油井 价值近百万
"He died a rich man." Oil wells and shit. Close to a million bucks.
一百万美元?
A million bucks?
是的 真他妈搞不懂那混蛋运气怎么那么好! 我靠 有你的份吗?
- Incredible how lucky some assholes get. - You going to see any of that?
三万五千块 他就留给我这么多
Thirty-five thousand. That's what he left me.
美元?
Dollars?
对
Yep.
太棒了 就像买中了赌马彩
That's great! That's like winning the sweepstakes.
不是吗?
Isn't it?
傻B啊你 你也不想想政府会怎么对我?
Dumb shit, what do you think the government will do to me?
还不得从我屁股上咬下一大块啊?
Take a big wet bite out of my ass is what.
可怜的拜伦 太他妈走运了!
Poor Byron.
奇耻大辱!
Terrible fucking luck, huh? Crying shame.
有人心情很坏哦
Some people really got it awful.
安迪 楞着干嘛? 看你的拖把 伙计!
Andy, are you nuts? Keep your eyes on your mop, man!
你是得上点税 但剩下的还够你...
You'll pay some tax, but you'll still end up...
没错 也许够买辆新车 但然后呢?
Yeah, maybe enough to buy a new car, and then what?
我得为新车上税 维修 保养
I got to pay tax on the car. Repair...
孩子们动不动缠着你带他们兜风
maintenance, kids pestering you to take them for a ride all the time.
如果年底算错了税金 还要掏自己的腰包
Then if you figure your tax wrong, you pay out of your own pocket.
我跟你讲! 山姆大叔...
I tell you! Uncle Sam...
会把手伸进你衬衣里捏你的奶头 直到捏紫为止
He puts his hand in your shirt and squeezes your tit till it's purple.
安迪!
Andy!
他不想活了 接着干啊
- Getting himself killed. - Keep tarring.
什么狗屁哥哥 呸!
Some brother. Shit!
哈德利先生
Mr. Hadley...
你信任你太太吗?
do you trust your wife?
噢 真有意思
Oh, that's funny.
我让你知道牙被打光后嘬我的鸡巴更有意思
You'll look funnier sucking my dick with no teeth.
我是说 你是不认为她对你有二心? 或者会背着你使坏?
What I mean is, do you think she'd go behind your back? Try to hamstring you?
让开点 米特 这鸟人想给自己来一出意外
Step aside, Mert. This fucker's having himself an accident.
他要把他推下去
He'll push him off!
如果你信任她 你就能保全那三万五千元!
If you trust her, you can keep...that 35 000.
- 你说什么? - 三万五千元!
- What did you say? - Thirty-five thousand.
- 三万五? - 全部!
- Thirty-five thousand? - All of it.
全部!?
All of it!?
- 一个子儿也不会少 - 你最好给我说明白点!
- Every penny. - You better start making sense.
你要保全这笔钱的话 就把它送给你妻子
If you want to keep it, give it to your wife.
国税局允许一次性赠与配偶最多六万美元
The IRS allows a one-time-only gift to your spouse for up to $ 60 000.
- 胡扯! 免税的吗? - 免税!
- Bullshit. Tax-free? - Tax-free.
国税局一毛钱都拿不走!
IRS can't touch one cent.
你是那个谋杀妻子的银行家 是吗?
You're that smart banker that killed his wife.
我凭什么相信你? 想让我来陪你坐牢吗?
Why should I believe you? So I can end up in here with you?
这是合法的 你可以去问国税局 他们也会这么说
It's legal. Ask the IRS. They'll say the same thing.
我也是一时糊涂才告诉你 我知道你本来也会去咨询的
I feel stupid telling you this. I'm sure you would have investigated.
还他妈轮不到你来教我怎么做!
I don't need you to tell me where the bear shit in the buckwheat.
当然不 但你需要有人替你申请免税
Of course not. But you do need someone to set it up for you.
那会让你破费 比如 你得请个律师
That'll cost you. A lawyer.
那帮洗了卵蛋的杂碎?
A bunch of ball-washing bastards!
我想我可以替你办理 说不定能替你省点钱
I suppose I could set it up for you. That would save you some money.
你只要找来表格 剩下的事交给我
You get the forms, I'll prepare them...
用不着花什么钱
nearly free of charge.
我想要的也就是给我的同事每人三瓶啤酒而已
I'd only ask three beers apiece for each of my coworkers.
"同事?" 你当你发达了啊?
"Coworkers." That's rich!
在外面干活的时候要是能有瓶啤酒喝
A man working outdoors feels more like a man...
那才更像个爷们儿 这只是我的一点想法
if he can have a bottle of suds. That's only my opinion...
长官!
sir.
你们这群呆子看什么看? 干你们的活!
What are you jimmies staring at?
干活干活!
Let's go! Work!
就这样 在49年春天的一个早晨
And that's how it came to pass...
在完工头一天的上午十点
that on the second-to-last day of the job...
一群在车间屋顶铺沥青的囚犯
the convict crew that tarred the factory roof in the spring of '49...
在屋顶围坐在一起
wound up sitting in a row at 10:00 in the morning...
享受着清凉的啤酒 还有"殷勤"的服务
drinking icy-cold beer, courtesy of the hardest screw...
而且都是拜肖申克州立监狱有史以来最狠的狱吏所赐
that ever walked a turn at Shawshank State Prison.
趁凉喝 女士们
Drink up while it's cold, ladies.
那二球还摆出一副很大度的样子
The colossal prick even managed to sound magnanimous.
我们品味着啤酒 阳光洒满臂膀 恍如自由人
We sat and drank with the sun on our shoulders and felt like free men.
感觉是在修整自家的屋项
We could have been tarring the roof of one of our own houses.
那一刻 我们就像造物主
We were the lords of all creation.
至于安迪
As for Andy...
他蜷坐在阴凉里 打发他的时光
he spent that break hunkered in the shade...
脸上带着奇异的微笑
a strange little smile on his face...
看我们喝他的啤酒
watching us drink his beer.
来一瓶吧?
Want a cold one?
不 谢谢 我戒酒了
No, thanks. I gave up drinking.
你可以说他是想讨好守卫
You could argue he done it to curry favor with the guards.
或者是想和我们拉关系
Or maybe make a few friends among us cons.
依我看
Me?
他这样做只是为了重温一下自由的时光
I think he did it just to feel normal again...
哪怕就那么一小会儿
if only for a short while.
我成王了
IKing me.
象棋 才是王者的游戏
- Chess. Now there's a game of kings. - What?
文明 战略 什么?
Civilized. Strategic.
还有一大套见鬼的规则 我讨厌规则
And a total fucking mystery. I hate it.
改天我教教你吧
Let me teach you someday.
好的
Sure.
我们可以一起弄个棋盘
We could get a board together.
你找对人了 我什么都能弄来 你知道噻?
You're talking to the right man. I can get things, right?
棋盘我们可以花钱买 棋子我想自己刻
We might do business on a board, and I'll carve the pieces myself.
白棋用雪花石膏 黑棋用皂石 你看怎么样?
One side in alabaster, one in soapstone. What do you think?
我看那得花好几年
I think it'll take years.
时间不是问题 问题是没有石头
Years I got. What I don't have are the rocks.
这院子里能捡到的都太小了
Pickings are pretty slim in the yard.
而且大多是鹅卵石
Pebbles, mostly.
安迪 我们得算是朋友了吧?
We're getting to be kind of friends, aren't we?
我想是的
Yeah, I guess.
我能问你个问题吗?
Can I ask you something?
你为什么做出那种事?
Why'd you do it?
我是被冤枉的 瑞德
I'm innocent, Red.
跟这儿其他人一样
Just like everybody else here.
你是怎么进来的?
What are you in for?
和你一样 谋杀
Murder. Same as you.
被冤枉的?
Innocent?
肖申克唯一有罪的人
Only guilty man in Shawshank.
她在哪儿唱歌呢?
Where's the canary?
你怎么知道的?
How did you know?
我知道什么了?
- How did I know what? - So you don't know.
这么说你不知道? 跟我来!
Come.
她就在里面
This is where the canary is.
听到我家里有女人唱歌很惊讶是吗?
Quite a surprise to hear a woman singing in my house, eh?
的确非常令我...
That's quite a...
惊讶
surprise.
瑞德
Red.
等一下 先别说话
Wait, wait.
她出场了
Here she comes.
我太喜欢看她摆弄头发那副骚样儿了
I like this part when she does that shit with her hair.
我知道 这个月已经看了三遍了
I know. I've seen it three times this month.
吉尔达 你打扮好了吗?
Gilda, are you decent?
我?
Me?
天呐 爱死啦
God, I love it.
我知道你有办法弄东西进来
I understand you're a man that knows how to get things.
这事儿大家一向都知道 你想要什么?
I'm known to locate certain things from time to time. What do you want?
- 丽塔·海华斯 - 什么?
- Rita Hayworth. - What?
你能搞到她吗?
Can you get her?
这么说你就是强尼了 久闻大名
So this is Johnny Farrel. I've heard a lot about you.
- 你得等几个星期 - 那么久?
- Take a few weeks. - Weeks?
我这分钟又没把她藏在裤裆里 抱歉我这么粗鲁
I don't have her stuffed down the front of my pants right now, sorry to say.
但我能拿到
But I'll get her.
放心好了!
Relax.
谢谢!
Thanks.
- 出去遛遛腿! - 可是我得换带子!
- Get out! - I got to change reels!
我叫你他妈的滚出去!
I said fuck off!
你不打算尖叫吗?
Ain't you going to scream?
我们做个了断吧!
Let's get this over with.
操 我鼻梁断了!
He broke my fucking nose!
现在
Now...
我要拉开拉链
I'm going to open my fly...
我给你吞什么你就吞什么
and you'll swallow what I give you to swallow.
然后是罗斯 你把他鼻子打坏了
Then you'll swallow Rooster's. You broke his nose.
他得找点补偿回来
He ought to have something to show for it.
你的命根子到我嘴里就会跟你分家
You put it in my mouth, you lose it.
不 你还没明白
No, you don't understand.
你敢那样 我就把这八英寸全部插到你耳朵里
Do that and I'll put all eight inches of this in your ear.
行啊 但你得知道大脑受到重创时
All right, but you should know that sudden, serious brain injury...
会让受害人拼命咬牙
causes the victim to bite down hard.
实话告诉你 这种咬劲儿之大
In fact, I hear the bite reflex is so strong...
得用铁棍才能把他的嘴巴撬开
they have to pry the victim's jaws open...with a crowbar.
你他妈从哪儿知道的?
Where do you get this shit?
看书看的
I read it.
不识字? 你这无知的杂种!
illiterate? You ignorant fuck!
哦宝贝儿
Honey!
你错了
You shouldn't!
伯格斯没把任何东西放进安迪的嘴里
Bogs didn't put anything in Andy's mouth.
他的同伙也没有
And neither did his friends.
他们只是把他打了个半死
What they did do is beat him within an inch of his life.
安迪在医务所躺了一个月
Andy spent a month in the infirmary.
伯格斯则被关了一周的小黑屋
Bogs spent a week in the hole.
伯格斯 时间到了
Time's up, Bogs.
遵命 头儿
It's your world, boss.
马上返回本人牢房 准备点名
Return to your cellblocks for evening count.
所有人犯返回牢房点名
All prisoners report for lock down.
干嘛?
What?
- 他要往哪儿跑? - 拽着脚脖子!
- Where's he going? - Grab his ankles.
不要! 不要!... 救命!
No! No!... Help!
从那以后 有两件事再也没发生过了
Two things never happened again after that.
姐妹们再也没碰过安迪一下
The Sisters never laid a finger on Andy again.
伯格斯再也没有站起来
And Bogs would never walk again.
他被送到北部一所低监护医院
They transferred him to a minimum-security hospital upstate.
据我所知 他的下半辈子
To my knowledge, he lived out the rest of his days...
都只能靠一根吃流食的吸管来维持了
drinking his food through a straw.
安迪从医务所出来时应该送他个见面礼
Andy could use a nice welcome back when he gets out of the infirmary.
好主意
Sounds good to us.
我们还欠着他的啤酒呢
I figure we owe him that much for the beer.
这小子喜欢下象棋
The man likes to play chess.
咱们给他找些石头吧
Let's get him some rocks.
伙计们
Guys!
我找到一块
I got one.
我找到一块 你们看
I got one. Look!
海伍德 那不是肥皂石 也不是雪花石膏
Heywood, that isn't soapstone! And it ain't alabaster either.
你当你是他妈的搞地质的吗?
What are you, a fucking geologist?
他说的没错 那真不是
He's right. It ain't.
- 那他妈这是什么玩意儿? - 那是马儿的苹果
- What the hell is it then? - It's a horse apple.
Bullshit：字面意思为"牛粪"
- 胡扯! - 不是牛粪 是风干的马粪
- Bullshit! - No, horseshit. Petrified.
妈的
Damn!
尽管开始不是太顺 但很快大伙便就轻架熟了
Despite a few hitches, the boys came through in fine style.
到安迪要回来的那个星期
And by the week Andy was due back...
我们找到的石头已经多得够他忙活一辈子了
we had enough rocks saved up to keep him busy till rapture.
同时 那个星期到了一大批货
Also got a big shipment in that week.
香烟
Cigarettes...
口香糖
chewing gum...
威士忌
sipping whisky...
印有裸体女人的扑克牌 随便你叫它什么吧
playing cards with naked ladies on them. You name it.
当然 最重要的东西
And of course, the most important item:
丽塔·海华斯她本人
Rita Hayworth herself.
欢迎归来 免费享用
注意 要查房了
Heads up. They're tossing cells.
Heads up. They're tossing cells!
119号
119.
123号
123.
《圣经》
站好
On your feet.
面朝墙壁
Face the wall.
向后转 面朝典狱长
Turn around and face the warden.
看见你在念经 我很欣慰
Pleased to see you reading this.
喜欢哪一段?
Any favorite passages?
"所以汝当警醒 因汝不知屋主何时到来!"
"Watch ye, therefore, for ye know not...when the master of the house cometh."
马可福音十三章三十五节
Mark 13:35.
我一直很喜欢这一段
I've always liked that one.
但我更喜欢...
But I prefer...
"我是世界之光 跟随我的人不会行于黑暗 还会拥有生命之光!"
" I am the light of the world. Ye that followeth me shall have the light of life."
约翰福音八章十二节
John, chapter 8, verse 12.
我听说你精通数字
I hear you're good with numbers.
非常好
How nice.
人应该有一技之长
Man should have a skill.
这是拿来干嘛的?
Explain this.
这是石垫 打磨石头用的
It's called a rock blanket. It's for shaping and polishing rocks.
我的一点小嗜好
A little hobby of mine.
相当干净
It's pretty clean.
有点违禁品 但不会导致严重后果
Some contraband here, but nothing to get in a twist over.
这我可不会同意
I can't say I approve of this.
但我想
But I suppose...
凡事总有例外
exceptions can be made.
锁门!
Lock them up!
差点忘了
I almost forgot.
我不能从你这儿带走这个
I'd hate to deprive you of this.
得救之道就在其中
Salvation lies within.
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
查房其实只是个借口
Tossing cells was just an excuse.
事实上 诺顿是想称称安迪的斤两
Truth is...Norton wanted to size Andy up.
主的审判将会迅速降临
我太太在教会做的
My wife made that in church group.
很漂亮 先生
Very nice, sir.
喜欢洗衣房的工作吗?
You enjoy working the laundry?
不 先生 不怎么喜欢
No, sir. Not especially.
或许我们可以找点别的更适合发挥你的学识的工作
Perhaps we can find something more...befitting a man of your education.
杰克 布鲁克斯呢?
Hey, Jake. Where's Brooks?
安迪
我就知道是你来了
I thought I heard you out here.
我被派到你这儿来了
I've been reassigned to you.
我知道 他们告诉我了
I know, they told me.
不会也是被踢过来的吧?
Ain't that a kick in the head?
好吧 我带你随便看看
Well, I'll give you the dime tour.
来吧
Come on.
就是这儿了
Well, here she is.
肖申克监狱图书馆
The Shawshank Prison Library.
《国家地理》
National Geographics...
《读者文摘》精华本
Reader's Digest condensed books...
美国著名小说家 作品逾百部 销量超过2亿册
路易斯·L·阿莫尔
and Louis L'Amour.
《展望》杂志
Look magazine.
美国著名侦探小说作家
厄尔·斯坦利·加德纳
Erle Stanley Gardners.
每天晚上我把车子装满 推出去遛一圈
Every evening I load up the cart and make my rounds.
在这块板子上记几个名字
I enter the names on this clipboard here.
司马光砸缸 小事一桩!
Easy, peasy, Japanese-y.
- 有问题吗? - 你作图书管理员有多久了?
- Any questions? - How long have you been librarian?
我1905年入狱 1912年他们安排我作图书管理员
I come here in '05, and they made me librarian in 1912.
你以前有助手吗?
And have you ever had an assistant?
没有 没什么要帮忙的 真的
No. Not much to it, really.
为什么现在? 为什么是我?
Why me? Why now?
这我可不知道
I don't know.
但有人来这儿和我作个伴我倒非常欢迎 杜弗瑞恩!
But it'd be nice to have some company down here.
就是他 你要找的人
That's him. That's the one.
我叫迪金斯
I'm Dekins.
我一直想...
I was thinking...
替我孩子的学业办一份信托基金
about setting up some kind of trust fund for my kids' educations.
我明白了
I see.
好吧...
Well...
让我们坐下来慢慢谈好吗?
Why don't we have a seat and talk it over.
布鲁克斯 你能找张纸还有铅笔吗?
Do you have a piece of paper and a pencil?
谢谢
Thanks.
那么...
So...
迪金斯先生
Mister Dekins...
接着安迪说 "迪金斯先生...
And then Andy says, "Mr. Dekins...
你想让你的儿子去哈佛还是耶鲁?"
do you want your sons to go to Harvard or Yale?"
他不可能那么说!
He didn't say that!
上帝可以作证
As God as my witness!
迪金斯愣了一下
Dekins blinked for a second...
然后傻笑起来 他甚至还握了安迪的手
then he laughed and actually shook Andy's hand.
扯淡吧!
My ass!
握他的手啊! 我跟你们讲 我高兴得差点尿裤子
Shook his hand, I tell you, I near soiled myself!
只要穿上西服打起领带 桌子上再来个扭着草裙舞的姑娘
All he needed was a suit and tie and a jiggly hula gal on his desk...
安迪就是"杜弗瑞恩先生"了 各位!
he'd have been "Mr. Dufresne " if you please.
安迪 交上新朋友了?
Making a few friends?
我只是一个可以提供可靠理财计划的犯人
I'm a convicted murderer who provides sound financial planning.
也就是个不错的宠物罢了
It's a wonderful pet to have.
至少你不用在洗衣房熬着了 对吧?
Got you out of the laundry, though.
也许还能多做点事情
It might do more than that.
扩大图书馆怎么样 弄些新书进来
How about expanding the library. Get some new books.
你有那能耐倒不如弄张台球桌进来
If you ask for something, ask for a pool table.
你打算怎么办? 我是说...
How do you expect to do that? I mean...
怎么弄来新书 "杜弗瑞恩先生" 不介意的话
get new books in here, "Mr. Dufresne, if you please."
我找典狱长要经费
I'll ask the warden for funds.
噢 孩子 孩子 我在这儿经历了六个典狱长
Six wardens have been through here in my tenure, and I've learned...
我学到一条亘古不变的普世真理
one immutable, universal truth:
当你要钱的时候 没有一个典狱长
Not one born whose asshole...
不把他们的屁眼绷的跟小军鼓一样紧的
wouldn't pucker up tighter than a snare drum when you ask for funds.
- 预算不够用 - 这我了解
- The budget's stretched thin as it is. - I see.
或许我可以写信向州参议员申请经费
Maybe I could write the state senate and request funds from them.
他们只会花纳税人的钱为监狱做三件事
They have only three ways to spend the taxpayers' money for prisons:
加高围墙 修建牢房 增派守卫!
More walls, more bars, more guards.
如果您准许 我想试试看 每周写一封信
I'd like to try, with permission. A letter a week.
- 他们不能永远不当回事儿 - 他们当然能!
- They can't ignore me forever. - Sure can.
但你要是写着高兴那就写吧
But you write your letters if it makes you happy.
我替你寄出去 怎么样?
I'll even mail them for you. How's that?
于是 安迪开始每周写一封信
So Andy started writing a letter a week...
就像他说的那样
just like he said.
诺顿说的也没错
And like Norton said...
安迪没得到过任何答复
Andy got no answers.
到次年四月时 安迪已经在帮肖申克的一半狱警报税了
The following April, he did tax returns for half the guards at Shawshank.
又过了一年 所有狱警都来找他帮忙
Year after that, he did them all...
包括典狱长的都由他处理了
including the warden's.
再过一年 他们甚至把狱警联赛的赛程安排在当年的报税期
Year after that, they rescheduled the intramural season...to coincide with tax season.
其它监狱球队的狱警们都带着报税单来打比赛
The guards on the opposing teams all remembered to bring their W-2s.
就是说莫尔斯比监狱...
So Moresby Prison...
配给你一支枪 但要你自己付钱
issued you a gun, but you paid for it.
对 手枪皮套也是
Right. The holster too.
那是免税的 你可以把这一项划掉
That's tax-deductible. You can write that off.
没错! 安迪完全像一个正规的会计师
Yes, sir! Andy was a regular cottage industry.
由于安迪一个人在报税期忙不过来 有必要配个帮手
In fact, it got so busy at tax time, he was allowed a staff.
瑞德 你可以拿一叠1040号表格给我吗?
Could you hand me a stack of 1040s?
每年能有一个月的时间离开木工车间 对我来说也相当不错
Got me out of the wood shop a month out of the year, and that was fine by me.
几年间 寄信那事儿他也从没耽误过
And still, he kept sending those letters.
瑞德 安迪 布鲁克斯出事了
It's Brooks.
看着门!
Watch the door.
- 求你了布鲁克斯 别他妈这么冲动! - 别过来!不要过来!
Please, Brooks. - Calm the fuck down. - Stay back! - Stay back, goddamn it! - What's going on?
- 怎么闹成这样? - 才还好好的 不知怎么的就冒把刀出来
One second he's fine, then out come the knives.
布鲁克斯 有话好好说 行吗?
We can talk about this, right?
没啥好说的 我他妈就是要给他一刀
There's nothing to talk about. I'll cut his fucking throat.
先等等 他把你怎么了?
What's he done to you?
这是他们逼我的!
It's what they done!
我没别的办法
I got no choice.
布鲁克斯你不会伤到海伍德的 大家都知道
You won't hurt Heywood. We all know that.
- 对吧 海伍德 你知道吧? - 是 没错 我知道
- Right, Heywood? - Sure.
你知道他为什么不会伤到你 因为他是你的朋友 布鲁克斯是个讲理的人
He's a friend of yours, and Brooks is a reasonable man.
- 对啊, 你说呢? - 是的!
Right, guys?
你把刀放下 布鲁克斯
So put the knife down. Look at me.
看着我布鲁克斯 把刀放下
Put the knife down.
布鲁克斯? 你看看他的脖子 看在上帝份儿上
Look at his neck, for God's sake.
布鲁克斯你看他的脖子 他流血了
Look at his neck. He's bleeding.
这是唯一可以...
It's the only way...
留在这儿的办法
they'd let me stay.
你这是糊涂了 你肯定不想这样
This is crazy. You don't want to do this.
松手 放下刀
Put it, put it down.
别紧张
Take it easy.
你不会有事的
You'll be all right.
他没事? 那我呢?
Him? What about me?
他妈的这个老疯子差点割断我的喉咙
Crazy old fool damn near cut my throat!
你刮胡子弄烂的口子也不止这么大
You've had worse from shaving.
你到底怎么把他惹毛的?
What did you do to set him off?
没惹啊 我过来和他道个别而已
Nothing. I come in here to say farewell.
你不知道啊? 他的假释批下来了
Ain't you heard? His parole's come through.
我真搞不懂这是怎么回事
I just don't understand what happened in there.
老家伙发疯了 就像一只痰盂里的老鼠
Old man's crazy as a rat in a tin shithouse.
海伍德你别没完没了
That's enough out of you.
- 我听说把你吓尿裤子了 - 去你的
- Heard he had you shitting your pants. - Fuck you.
不说话会死啊!
Would you knock it off.
布鲁克斯没发神经
Brooks ain't no bug.
他只不过是...他只不过是被体制化了罢了
He's just institutionalized.
体制化个鸡毛
"Institutionalized " my ass.
老头儿在这儿呆了五十年了 海伍德 五十年!
The man's been in here 50 years, Heywood, 50 years!
他就认识这个地方
This is all he knows.
在这儿 他是个有地位的人
In here, he's an important man...
一个有教养的人
an educated man.
到了外面 他什么都不是
Outside, he's nothing.
只是个双手患有关节炎的假释犯
Just a used-up con with arthritis in both hands.
可能连一张图书馆的借书证都申请不到
Probably couldn't get a library card if he tried.
你听懂我说的话没有?
You know what I'm trying to say?
瑞德 我听懂了 你说的全是屁话
I do believe you're talking out of your ass.
信不信随你大小便
You believe whatever you want.
但我得告诉你 这些围墙很吊诡
But I tell you these walls are funny.
刚来的时候 你会恨它
First you hate them.
慢慢你就会习惯它
Then you get used to them.
日子久了...
Enough time passes...
你会发现你离不开它
you get so you depend on them.
那就是被体制化了
That's "institutionalized."
操! 我永远不可能爱上这堵破墙
Shit. I could never get like that. - Oh, yeah?
是吗? 这话等你在这儿呆够布鲁克斯那么久再说
Wait till you've been here as long as Brooks.
太他妈对了
Goddamn right.
他们把你送进来渡过余生
They send you here for life...
那也正是他们想要剥夺的
that's exactly what they take.
总之 去日无多
Part that counts, anyway.
我不能再照顾你了 杰克
I can't take care of you no more, Jake.
你现在走吧
You go on now.
你自由了
You're free.
布鲁克斯 祝你好运
Good luck, Brooksie.
亲爱的伙计们
Dear fellas:
我没法相信外面的东西怎么会跑那么快
I can't believe how fast things move on the outside.
老头 找死啊?
Watch it, old-timer! Want to get killed?
我小时候就见过一次汽车
I saw an automobile once when I was a kid...
但现在这东西无处不在
but now they're everywhere.
全世界都他妈忙得不可开交
The world went and got itself in a big damn hurry.
假释委员会安排我住在一家小旅馆 叫 Brewster
The parole board got me into this halfway house...called "The Brewster"...
还有一份差事 在Food-Way超市替顾客打包
and a job...bagging groceries at the Food-Way.
活儿很忙 我很努力
It's hard work and I try to keep up...
但我这双手总是酸痛不已
but my hands hurt most of the time.
让你的人给我多套一个袋子
Make sure your man double-bags.
上回给我的单层袋子底儿差点烂完了
Last time, the bottom near came out.
按那位女士说的多套一个袋子 懂了吗?
Make sure you double-bag like the lady says. Understand?
是的 先生 我会的
Yes, sir. Surely will.
看得出那经理对我不太感冒
I don't think the store manager likes me very much.
有时下了班以后 我会去公园里喂喂鸽子
Sometimes after work, I go to the park and feed the birds.
我一直在念叨
I keep thinking...
杰克说不定会飞来和我打个招呼
Jake might just show up and say hello.
但它从没来过
But he never does.
我希望 不管在哪 它都能过的好 交到新朋友
I hope, wherever he is, he's doing okay and making new friends.
夜里我总是睡不好
I have trouble sleeping at night.
老是做恶梦 身体像一直往下掉
I have bad dreams like I'm falling.
醒来时万分恐惧
I wake up scared.
经常要想一会儿才知道自己在哪儿
Sometimes it takes me a while to remember where I am.
也许我该搞把枪把 Food- Way抢了 好让他们送我回家
Maybe I should get a gun and rob the Food-Way so they'd send me home.
顺便给那个经理来一枪 就当是锦上添花
I could shoot the manager while I was at it. Sort of like a bonus.
可是我已经太老了 再也干不了这种蠢事了
I guess I'm too old for that sort of nonsense anymore.
我不喜欢这地方
I don't like it here.
我觉得很疲惫 不想继续这样成天提心吊胆的 我决定...
I'm tired of being afraid all the time. I've decided...
不这么耗着了
not to stay.
我想他们是不会大惊小怪的
I doubt they'll kick up any fuss...
为我这种老不死的犯不上
not for an old crook like me.
布鲁克斯在这儿住过
我猜他们是不会大惊小怪的 为我这种老不死的犯不上
"I doubt they'll kick up any fuss, not for an old crook like me.
另外 还得向海伍德道个歉 请原谅我上次用刀顶着你脖子
P.S. Tell Heywood I'm sorry I put a knife to his throat.
这样我也就安心了 布鲁克斯
No hard feelings. Brooks."
他应该死在这儿的
He should have died in here.
你他妈搞什么东东?
What the fuck have you done?
简直他妈乱成一锅粥了
It's a goddamn mess, I'll tell you that.
- 这些都是什么? - 我怎么知道 全他妈是寄给你的
- What's all this? - You tell me. They're addressed to you.
看看吧
Take it.
"亲爱的杜弗瑞恩先生
"Dear Mr. Dufresne:
应阁下来函所请事由 州政府特拨付
In response to your inquiries...
贵图书馆项目经费一笔...
the state has allocated the enclosed funds for your library project."
200美元...
This is $ 200.
此外 州立图书馆亦慷慨捐助
"In addition, the library district has generously responded...
旧书暨杂物一批
with a donation of used books and sundries.
我们相信上述款物足以满足阁下所需 此事就此告一段落
We trust this will fill your needs. We now consider the matter closed.
恳请阁下勿复来函"
Please stop sending us letters."
典狱长回来之前清理干净
Clear all this out before the warden gets back.
知道了
Yes, sir.
干得好安迪!
Good for you, Andy.
哇哦!
Wow!
只用了六年时间
It only took six years.
现在开始 我每星期写两封信
From now on, I'll write two letters a week instead of one.
你可真够倔的 你最好照他说的把这儿收拾干净
I believe you're crazy enough. Get this stuff out...like he said.
我现在去撇大条
I've got to pinch a loaf.
等我出来的时候
When I come back...
不想再见到这些东西 好吗?
this is all gone, all right?
费加罗的婚礼
安迪 那是什么声音?
Do you hear that?
杜弗瑞恩?
Dufresne!
安迪 让我出去!
Andy, let me out!
安迪?
Andy.
我至今仍不知晓那两个意大利娘们儿在唱什么
I have no idea to this day what those two Italian ladies were singing about.
话说回来 我也不想知道
Truth is, I don't want to know.
有些东西是无需言传的
Some things are best left unsaid.
我更相信那是因为它的美
I like to think it was something so beautiful...
超出了语言所能形容的范畴
it can't be expressed in words...
它美得让你为之心碎
and makes your heart ache because of it.
我只能告诉你 那声音直入云霄
I tell you, those voices soared...
比这个灰暗角落里任何人所能梦想到的都更高更远
higher and farther than anybody in a gray place dares to dream.
就像一只美丽的小鸟 飞进我们乏味的牢笼
It was like a beautiful bird flapped into our drab cage...
高墙因之消逝于无形之间
and made those walls dissolve away.
就是那一刻
And for the briefest of moments...
每一个关在肖申克的失足者都触摸到了自由
every last man at Shawshank felt free.
但这却惹得典狱长大发雷霆
It pissed the warden off something awful.
把门打开!
Open the door.
开门!
Open it up!
杜弗瑞恩 给我开门!
Dufresne, open this door!
把它关掉!
Turn that off!
我警告你 杜弗瑞恩! 把它关掉!
I am warning you. Turn that off!
小兔乖乖! ; )
该我收拾你了!
You're mine now.
安迪的惊艳一枪给他带来了两周的禁闭
Andy got two weeks in the hole for that little stunt.
站起来!
On your feet.
- 看看谁来了? - 艺术大师!
- Hey, look who's here. - Maestro!
美国乡村摇滚音乐的标志性人物
你就不能放点好听的吗 嗯? 比如汉克·威廉姆斯?
You couldn't play something good, huh? Like Hank Williams?
我还没来得及接受点播 他们就冲进来了
They broke the door down before I could take requests.
- 两个星期 犯得上吗? - 我经历过最轻松的一段时光!
- Was it worth two weeks? - Easiest time I ever did.
扯淡 在这破地方就没轻松时光可言 那小黑屋里呆一周就像一年!
- Bullshit! No such thing as easy time in the hole. - A week in the hole is like a year.
是他妈像一年! 我有莫扎特先生陪我!
- Damn straight.  - I had Mr. Mozart to keep me company.
他们还能让你背台电唱机进去啊?
So they let you tote that record player down there, huh?
它在我脑子里
It was in here.
在我心里
In here.
这就是音乐的美妙所在 他们...
That's the beauty of music. They...
无法把它从你这儿夺走
can't get that from you.
你们对音乐没有这种感受吗?
Haven't you ever felt that way about music?
我年轻那会儿曾经吹过口琴
Well, I played a mean harmonica as a younger man.
进来以后也就没兴趣了
Lost interest in it, though.
在大牢里没多大意义
Didn't make much sense in here.
这儿才是它最有价值的地方
Here's where it makes the most sense.
有了它你才不会忘记
You need it so you don't forget.
忘记?
Forget?
忘记这世上...有一些地方...不是用石头围起来的
Forget that there are...places...
在你内心深处...有一些东西...
in the world that aren't made out of stone. There's something...inside...
是他们夺不走...摸不到的 只属于你一个人
that they can't get to...that they can't touch. That's yours.
你在说什么?
What are you talking about?
希望
Hope.
希望?
我坦白告诉你 我的朋友
Let me tell you something, my friend.
希望是一种危险品
Hope is a dangerous thing.
希望使人疯狂
Hope can drive a man insane.
它在大牢里没有用
It's got no use on the inside.
你得学会接受现实
You'd better get used to that idea.
像布鲁克斯那样?
Like Brooks did?
坐吧!
Sit down.
你因被判终身监禁己在此服刑三十年了
Says here that you've served 30 years of a life sentence.
你认为你已经改过自新了吗?
You feel you've been rehabilitated?
是的 先生
Oh, yes, sir.
毫无疑问
Without a doubt.
说实话我已经完全改变了
I can honestly say I'm a changed man.
我不会再危害社会
No danger to society here.
向上帝保证
God's honest truth.
绝对改过自新了
Absolutely rehabilitated.
驳回
三十年
Thirty years.
老天 说起来...
Jesus, when you say it like that...
不知道怎么过去的是吧?
You wonder where it went.
我是不知道我这十年是怎么过去的
I wonder where 10 years went.
这个...
Here.
是给你假释被拒的小礼物
A little parole rejection present.
打来看看!
Go ahead and open it.
从你同行那儿买的
Went through one of your competitors.
希望你不会介意 我是想给你个惊喜
I hope you don't mind. I wanted it to be a surprise.
说实话 真的很漂亮
It's very pretty, indeed.
谢谢你
Thank you.
你打算吹吗?
You going to play it?
不
No.
现在不打算
Not right now.
进囚室!
Roll in!
新一代美女 纪念你的十周年 瑞德
熄灯!
Lights out!
安迪说到做到
Andy was as good as his word.
他开始每周写两封信
He wrote two letters a week instead of one.
1959年 州参议员终于认识到
In 1959, the state senate finally clued in to the fact...
一张200美元的支票打发不了他
they couldn't buy him off with just a $ 200 check.
州预算委员会投票决定每年拨付款项500元
Appropriations Committee voted an annual payment of $500...
好让他就此闭嘴
just to shut him up.
之后安迪所做的则更让我们瞠目结舌
And you'd be amazed how far Andy could stretch it.
他跟读书会和慈善组织接洽
He made deals with book clubs, charity groups.
论磅买来大量二手书籍
He bought remaindered books by the pound...
《金银岛》
Treasure Island.
罗伯特·路易斯...
Robert Louis...
斯蒂文森
Stevenson.
小说 探险类
Fiction, adventure.
下一本是什么?
What's next?
我这儿是《汽车修理》...
I got here Auto Repair...
和《肥皂雕刻》
and Soap Carving.
职业技术与爱好 属"教育"类 在你后面
Trade skills and hobbies. Under "Educational " behind you.
《基叔山恩仇记》
Count of Monte Crisco.
那是"基督山" 你个笨蛋!
That's "Cristo " you dumb shit.
作者是亚历山大...
By Alexandree...
大种马 (Dum-ass)
Dum-ass.
"大马屁?" (Dumb ass)
Dumb ass.
"大马屁?"
Dumb ass?
大仲马 (Dumas) 知道那是讲什么的吗?
Dumas. IKnow what that's about?
你一定喜欢 它讲的是一次越狱
You'd like it. It's about a prison break.
那我们应该把它归到"教育"类 对吧?
We ought to file that under "Educational" too, oughtn't we?
我们几个则尽我们所能全力帮忙
The rest of us did our best to pitch in when and where we could.
到了肯尼迪遇刺那一年
By the year Kennedy was shot...
安迪已经把一间散发着松节油味道的储藏室
Andy had transformed a storage room smelling of turpentine...
改造成了新英格兰地区最好的的监狱图书馆
into the best prison library in New England...
甚至找得到Hank Williams的精选集唱片
complete with a fine selection of Hank Williams.
那一年也是典狱长诺顿
That was also when Warden Norton...
提出著名的"出监服刑"计划的一年
instituted his famous "Inside Out" program.
也许你看到过这件事的新闻
You may remember reading about it.
当时曾充斥各类报纸 他的照片还上过《展望》杂志
It made the papers and got his picture in Look magazine.
这不是放任自流
It's no free ride...
而是一种真正的 有进步意义的
but rather a genuine progressive advance...
服刑和改造模式
in corrections and rehabilitation.
我们的服刑人员 在适当的监管下
Our inmates, properly supervised...
走出这堵高墙 在外面工作
will be put to work outside these walls...
提供各种形式的公共服务
performing all manner of public service.
他们将懂得诚实劳动的价值
These men can learn the value...
同时他们为社会所提供的服务
of an honest day's labor and provide a service to the community...
对纳税人而言 可将开销降至最低
at a bare minimum of expense to Mr. And Mrs. John Q. Taxpayer.
当然 诺顿不会跟报界说明
Of course he didn't tell the press...
"最低开销"其实是个相当不靠谱的噱头
that "bare minimum of expense" is a fairly loose term.
他有一百种不同的办法暗渡陈仓
There are 100 different ways to skim off the top.
人工 材料 你想怎么算就怎么算
Men, materials, you name it.
哦上帝 金钱就这样滚滚而来!
And oh, my Lord, how the money rolled in!
这样下去 我就没法干了
At this rate, you'll put me out of business.
你守着这些工奴 全城的承包商都没法跟你杀价
With this pool of slave labor, you can underbid any contractor in town.
我们这是在为社会提供有价值的服务
We're providing a valuable community service.
记者当然爱听你这套话 可我还得养家糊口呢
That's fine for the papers, but I've got a family to feed.
山姆...山姆 我们处的时间也不短了
We go back a long way.
我真的需要这份高速公路合同 如果拿不到 说实话我就废了
I need this highway contract. I don't get it and I go under. That's a fact.
你尝尝这些馅饼
You have some of this fine pie...
我老婆特意为你烤的 你就帮帮我吧
my missus made for you. You think about that.
换我是你的话对这个合同不会太担心
I wouldn't worry too much about this contract.
我已经把人手派去干别的了
I already got my boys committed elsewhere.
请一定替我谢谢你太太烤这么好的馅饼
You be sure and thank Maisie for this fine pie.
每一笔暗箱操作
And behind every shady deal...
赚来的每一块钱
behind every dollar earned...
都是由安迪经手做账的
there was Andy, keeping the books.
两笔存款
Two deposits.
缅因州国家银行和新英格兰第一银行 照例办夜间存款
Maine National and New England First. Night drops as always, sir.
把我东西送到洗衣房 两套衣服要干洗 还有古董架上那个包
Get my stuff to the laundry. Two suits for dry-clean and a bag of whatnot.
告诉他们如果再把我的衬衫浆过了头 我就过去教教他们!
If they over-starch my shirts again, they'll hear from me.
- 我看上去怎么样? - 非常好!
How do I look?
波特兰大道有个大型慈善晚会 州长会去!
- Very nice. - Big charity to-do up Portland way. Governor will be there.
剩下这些给你吧?
You want the rest of this?
女人只能烤出恶心的东西
Woman can't bake worth shit.
谢谢你 先生
Thank you, sir.
我听说这样的馅饼他收了不少
He's got his fingers in a lot of pies, from what I hear.
有些手段你做梦都想不到 层层的回扣
He's got scams you haven't even dreamed of. IKickbacks on his kickbacks.
黑钱像河一样流过这里
A river of dirty money running through here.
但他迟早得解释钱是从哪儿来的
Sooner or later, he'll have to explain where it came from.
这就是他用得着我的地方了
That's where I come in.
我让这些钱流通 洗白 汇集
I channel it. Filter it. Funnel it.
股票、证券、国库券...
Stocks, securities, tax-free municipals.
我把钱撒出去 等它们回来的时候...
I send it out into the real world, and when it comes back...
- 干净得就像个处女穴 嗯? - 比那更干净
- Clean as a virgin's honeypot, huh? - Cleaner.
到诺顿退休的时候 我已让他成为百万富翁了
By the time Norton retires, I'll have made him a millionaire.
如果被抓住的话 他岂不是得在这儿给自己编个号儿啊?
If they ever catch on, he'll wind up in here wearing a number himself.
我还以为你很信得过我呢
I thought you had more faith in me than that.
我知道你很能干 但那么多文件总会留下蛛丝马迹
I know you're good, but all that paper leaves a trail.
如果有人想追究 FBI 国税局...
Now anybody gets curious, FBI, IRS...
无论如何
whatever.
总会有人被扯出来
It'll lead to somebody.
那当然 但不会是我 当然也不会是典狱长
Sure it is, but not to me, and certainly not to the warden.
好吧 是谁呢?
All right, who?
兰度·史蒂文!
Randall Stevens.
那是谁?
Who?
沉默寡言的搭档
The "silent" silent partner.
他是那个有罪的人 帐户的所有者
He's the guilty one, the man with the bank accounts.
是洗钱流程的起点
It's where the filtering process starts.
如果有人追查 顶多查到他那儿
They trace anything, it'll just lead to him.
但他是什么人?
But who is he?
他是一个幻影 幽灵 是兔子哈维的二表哥
He's a phantom, an apparition. Second cousin to Harvey the Rabbit.
我凭空...变出来的!
I conjured him...out of thin air.
他只是个活在文件中的人
He doesn't exist, except on paper.
但是你不可能就这么造个人出来
You can't just make a person up.
当然可以 只要你知道制度的运作模式
Sure you can, if you know how the system works.
更令你吃惊的是邮件就能帮你做到
It's amazing what you can accomplish by mail.
史蒂文先生有出生证明书
Mr. Stevens has a birth certificate...
驾驶执照和社保号码
driver's license, Social Security.
你别忽悠我!
You're shitting me.
他们追查帐户 就像是去雕刻一个我想象中的虚幻物
If they trace any accounts, they'll wind up chasing...a figment of my imagination.
靠 果然精英人士!
Well, I'll be damned!
我是不是早就说过你很能干?
Did I say you were good?
荷兰画家 17世纪欧洲最伟大的画家之一
妈的 你简直是当代伦布兰特
Shit, you are Rembrandt.
讽刺的是
The funny thing is...
在外面 我是个正直的人 宁折不弯
on the outside, I was an honest man, straight as an arrow.
却不得不到监狱里来作一个骗子
I had to come to prison to be a crook.
你苦恼过吗?
Ever bother you?
点子不是我出的 我只是处理收益
I don't run the scams. I just process the profits.
是条很好的分界线 也许是
A fine line, maybe...
好在我还建起了图书馆
but I also built that library...
在那儿帮兄弟们拿到高中文凭
and used it to help guys get their high school diploma.
否则你以为他凭什么让我做这些事?
Why do you think he lets me do all that?
让你开心 好帮他运作"洗衣房"...
Keep you happy and doing the laundry.
洗的是钱而不是床单而已
Money instead of sheets.
是的 好让我心甘情愿 算是交换条件
Well, I work cheap. That's the tradeoff.
汤米·威廉姆斯被送进肖申克来是在1965年
Tommy Williams came to Shawshank in 1965...
被判两年徒刑 罪名是"B&E"
on a two-year stretch for B & E.
就是破门入室闯进你家的意思
That's breaking and entering to you.
警察在一家JC Penney便利店后门发现他抱台电视机正想开溜
Cops caught him sneaking TV sets out the back door of a JC Penney.
小混混
Young punk.
"摇滚"先生
Mr. Rock 'n' Roll...
目空一切
cocky as hell.
快点 老头子们 黏糊得跟糖浆一样
Come on, old boys. Moving like molasses!
你们拖我后腿嘛!
Making me look bad.
我们马上就喜欢上他了
We liked him immediately.
我从门里退出来 就这样抱着电视机
I'm backing out the door and I got the TV like this.
那东西太大了 我他妈啥都看不到 然后我听到一个声音
A big old thing. I couldn't see shit. Then I hear this voice.
"别动 小子 把手举过头顶!"
"Freeze, kid, hands in the air."
我只好站在那里 抱着电视机 那声音又说
I was standing there, holding onto that TV. Finally the voice says:
"你听到我的话了吗? " 我说 "是的先生 我也想举手"
"You hear what I said, boy?" I say, " Yes, sir. I did.
"但如果我把这东西丢下 你会加告我毁坏财物的"
But if I drop this, you get me on destruction of property too."
嘿 你在卡士曼蹲过 是吗?
You done some stretch in Cashman, right?
是的 那儿要好过得多
Yeah, that was an easy piece of time, let me tell you.
周末休假 工作也有条理
Weekend furloughs. Work programs.
不像这里 看来你在新英格兰哪儿都蹲过
Not like here. Sounds like you done time all over.
我十三岁开始就到处蹲班房了
I've been in and out since I was 13.
你随便说个地方 没准我就呆过
Name it, chances are I've been there.
也许你应该试试改行了
Perhaps you should try a new profession.
我的意思是...
What I mean is...
干小偷你没什么前途了 你最好试试干点别的
you're not a very good thief. You should try something else.
是吗? 那你鸡巴又有什么拿手活儿 大佬?
Yeah, what the hell you know about it, Capone?
你怎么也在这儿关着呢?
What are you in for?
我吗?
Me?
我被律师设计了
A lawyer fucked me.
这儿所有人都是被冤枉的 你不知道吗?
Everybody's innocent in here. Don't you know that?
后来知道 汤米有个年轻妻子和刚出生的女儿
As it turned out, Tommy had himself a young wife and a new baby girl.
也许他想到她们流落街头
Maybe he thought of them on the streets...
闺女长大了还没见过她老爸
or his child growing up not knowing her daddy.
不管为什么 总之
Whatever it was...
这孩子坐不住了
something lit a fire under that boy's ass.
我想也许应该试一下考个高中文凭
Thought I might try for my high school equivalency.
听说你已经帮了好多人考取了
Hear you helped a couple of fellas with that.
我不想在失败者身上浪费时间 汤米
I don't waste time with losers, Tommy.
我再也不是他妈的失败者了
I ain't no goddamn loser.
- 是吗? - 是的!
- You mean that? - Yeah.
你是说真的?
You really mean that?
是的 先生 绝对认真
Yes, sir, I do.
好 因为我们要做...
Good. Because if we do this...
就要有始有终 百分之一百不能半途而废
we do it all the way, a hundred percent, nothing half-assed.
问题是 你瞧...
Thing is, see...
我不太识字!
I don't read so good.
这样啊?
"Well."
你不太识字...
You don't read...
好吧
so well.
我们就从识字开始!
We'll get to that.
就这样 安迪把汤米收至帐下
So Andy took Tommy under his wing.
从ABC开始带他
Started walking him through his ABC's.
汤米学得很快
Tommy took to it pretty well too.
这孩子从没发现自己的聪明所在
Boy found brains he never knew he had.
没过多久 安迪开始教他必修课程
Before long, Andy started him on his course requirements.
他非常喜欢这个小子
He really liked the kid.
帮一个年轻人走出泥潭让他很快乐
Gave him a thrill to help a youngster crawl off the shit heap.
但那并不是唯一的原因
But that wasn't the only reason.
监狱里的时间过得很缓慢
Prison time is slow time.
你需要找些事情消磨时间
So you do what you can to keep going.
有人收集邮票
Some fellas collect stamps.
有人用火柴棍儿搭房子
Others build matchstick houses.
安迪建起了图书馆
Andy built a library.
现在他需要一个新的计划
Now he needed a new project.
那就是汤米
Tommy was it.
那和他多年来雕磨石头的原因一样
It was the same reason he spent years shaping and polishing those rocks.
和他把梦中女郎挂在墙上的原因一样
The same reason he hung his fantasy girlies on the wall.
在监狱里
In prison...
你得用杂七杂八的事情把脑子塞满
a man will do most anything to keep his mind occupied.
1966年 就在汤米刚要参加考试的时候
By 1966, right about the time Tommy was getting ready to take his exams...
美国电影女星
可爱的 拉蔻儿出现了
it was lovely Raquel.
时间到!
Time.
怎么样了?
Well?
怎么样? 狗屎样!
Well, it's for shit.
我白白花了一年时间在这堆狗屎上面
I wasted a whole year of my time with this bullshit.
也许不是你想的那么糟
It's probably not that bad.
没错 比我想的还要糟 我他妈一道题都没答对 就像在考中文!
I didn't get a thing right. It might as well have been in Chinese.
看看你能得多少分
Let's see how the score comes out.
我来告诉你能得他妈多少分!
I'll tell you how the goddamn score comes out.
两分! 正中篮筐!
Two points, right there!
那就是你想要的他妈的分数!
There's your goddamn score!
去他妈的猫爬上树 5乘以5是25!
Goddamn cats crawling up trees, 5 times 5 is 25...
去他妈的学堂!
Fuck this place!
我操!
Fuck it!
我觉得糟透了
I feel bad.
我叫他失望了
I let him down.
没有的事 小子
That's crap, kid.
他以你为荣!
He's proud of you.
我们是多年的朋友 我比任何人都了解他
We're old friends, I know him as good as anybody.
聪明人 不是吗?
Smart fellow, ain't he?
聪明之极 没进来以前是个银行家
Smart as they come. He was a banker on the outside.
他到底为什么被抓进来?
What's he in here for anyway?
谋杀!
Murder.
怎么可能?
The hell, you say.
人不可貌相!
You wouldn't think it to look at the guy.
他老婆和一个什么高尔夫教练被他捉奸在床 俩贱人一块儿解决了
Caught his wife in bed with some golf pro. Greased them both.
怎么了?
What?
大约四年前
About four years ago...
我在汤玛斯监狱蹲两到三年的徒刑
I was in Thomaston on a two-to-three stretch.
我偷了辆汽车...那是件很傻B的事
I stole a car. It was a dumb-fuck thing to do.
在出狱前六个月 新来了一个家伙和我关一间房...
About six months left to go...I get a new cellmate in.
艾马·布莱奇
Elmo Blatch.
一个强壮 暴躁的混蛋
Big, twitchy fucker.
谁见了都躲着走的人渣 见过那种人吧?
IKind of roomie you pray you don't get. You know what I'm saying?
判了六到十二年 持械入室盗窃
Six-to-twelve, armed burglary.
吹牛B说自己干了几百票案子
Said he pulled hundreds of jobs.
你不知道他有多得瑟 听你放个响屁他能蹦三尺高
Hard to believe, high-strung as he was. You cut a loud fart, he jumped three feet.
整天逼得得个不停 东拉西扯 他嘴巴就没闲过
Talked all the time too. That's the other thing. He never shut up.
吹他去过的地方 干过的案子 上过的女人
Places he'd been in...jobs he'd pulled, women he fucked.
甚至杀过的人...
Even people he killed.
那些跟他"废鸡巴话"的人!
People who "gave him shit."
那就是他杀人的理由
That's how he put it.
有天晚上 我半开玩笑地问他
So one night, like a joke...
我说 艾马 你都杀过谁?
I say to him, "Elmo, who did you kill?"
于是他说...
So he says:
有次我想搞一票 就去一家俱乐部跑堂
I got me this job one time, busing tables at a country club...
这样可以摸清那些有钱的屌人的路子
so I could case all these big rich pricks that come in.
后来我看准了一个家伙
So I pick out this guy...
晚上摸进他家
go in one night...
翻值钱的东西
and do his place.
他醒过来
He wakes up...
跟我废鸡巴话
and gives me shit.
于是我就把他给做了
So I killed him.
还有跟他在一起的一个漂亮婊子
Him and this tasty bitch he was with.
最绝的是
And that's the best part.
那婊子跟那个屌人操逼 那个高尔夫教练
She's fucking this prick, see...
但她其实是个有夫之妇
this golf pro, but she's married to some other guy.
老公是个牛B的银行家
Some hotshot banker.
那家伙后来成了替罪羊
And he's the one they pinned it on.
我得说这是我听过的最令人吃惊的故事
I have to say that's the most amazing story I ever heard.
我吃惊的是你竟然当真了
What amazes me most is you'd be taken in by it.
先生?
Sir?
很明显威廉姆斯非常仰慕你
It's obvious this fellow Williams is impressed with you.
他知道你的不幸遭遇后当然想让你振作起来
He hears your tale of woe and naturally wants to cheer you up.
他还年轻 不太聪明
He's young, not terribly bright.
不知道他将陷你于何种境地 这并不奇怪
It's not surprising he wouldn't know what a state he put you in.
先生 他讲的是事实
Sir, he's telling the truth.
就当有布莱奇这个人存在
Let's say for the moment this Blatch does exist.
你想他会跪下来 哭着说"是我做的 我坦白"
You think he'd just fall to his knees and cry, " Yes, I did it. I confess.
"方便的话 给我判个终身监禁吧"
By the way, add a life term to my sentence."
但有了汤米的证词 我的案子可以重审
With Tommy's testimony, I can get a new trial.
前提是布莱奇还关在那儿
That's assuming Blatch is still there.
也许他现在已经获释了
Chances are, he'd be released by now.
他们应该有他最近的住址
They'd have his last known address.
这是个机会 对吗?
It's a chance, isn't it?
你怎么会如此愚钝?
How can you be so obtuse?
什么?
What?
你刚才说我什么?
What did you call me?
愚钝 你是故意的吧?
Obtuse. Is it deliberate?
小子 你忘记你的身份了!
You're forgetting yourself.
俱乐部会有他以前的考勤卡 履历表...
The country club will have his old timecards.
报税单 都写着他名字的
Records, W-2s with his name on them.
杜弗瑞恩 你要继续幻想的话 那是你的事
If you want to indulge this fantasy, it's your business.
不要拿来烦我 谈话到此结束
Don't make it mine. This meeting is over.
如果我出去 我绝不会提起这里的事情
If I got out, I'd never mention what happens here.
为你洗钱我也脱不了干系
I'd be as indictable as you for laundering that money.
不许在我面前提钱! 你这个婊子养的!
Don't ever mention money to me, you sorry son of a bitch!
不许在这间办公室提!
Not in this office...
不许在任何地方提!
not anywhere. Get in here, now!
我只是想让你放心 没别的意思 进来! 马上!
I just wanted to put you at ease, that's all.
- 禁闭室! 一个月! - 是! 长官!
Solitary. A month.
你这是怎么了?
What's wrong with you?
把他带出去!
Get him out of here.
这是还我清白的机会!
This is my chance to get out!
这是我的人生! 你明白吗?
It's my life! Understand?!
带他出去! 带他出去!
Get him out!
一个月禁闭!
A month in the hole.
这他妈是我听过的最长的禁闭了!
That's the longest stretch I ever heard of.
这都是我的错!
It's all my fault.
屁话!
Bullshit.
人不是你杀的 案子也不是你判的
You didn't pull the trigger or convict him.
你是说安迪是被冤枉的?
Are you saying Andy is innocent?
我是说 他真是被冤枉的?
I mean, for real innocent?
看样子是!
It looks that way.
苍天啊!
Sweet Jesus.
他关进来有多久了?
How long has he been here now?
1947 那是多少 19年!
1947. What is that? Nineteen years.
- 威廉姆斯? - 在这儿!
- Williams, Thomas. - Yeah, over here.
这是什么?
What you got?
教育部!
Board of Education.
那老鬼把卷子寄出去了
That son of a bitch mailed it.
你打算打开看看? 还是在这儿愣着?
You going to open it or stand there with your thumb up your butt?
在这儿愣着听起来好一点
Thumb up my butt sounds better.
斯基兹...别这样...还给我...
Skeets, come on. Give me that, you shithead.
弗洛伊德 给我
Floyd, come on.
瑞德!
帮帮忙把它扔了 好吗?
Will you throw that away, please?
喔 妈的!
Well, shit.
那孩子过了 平均C+
The kid passed. C + average.
你大概在等这消息
Thought you'd like to know.
典狱长要找你谈话
Warden wants to talk.
在外面?
Out here?
他是这么说的!
That's what the man said.
典狱长?
Warden?
汤米!
汤米 我要你对这次谈话的内容绝对保密!
I'm asking you to keep this conversation just between us.
此事相当棘手!
I feel awkward enough as it is.
这儿有人的判决似乎出了问题
We got a situation here.
我想你也意识到了这一点
I think you can appreciate that.
是的! 先生 这我能看出来!
Yes, sir. I sure can.
说实话 孩子 这件事让我坐卧不安
I tell you, son, this thing really came along and knocked my wind out.
夜不能寐 真的!
It's got me up nights. That's the truth.
什么是该做的正确的事?
The right thing to do...
时常难于厘清
sometimes it's hard to know what that is.
你能理解吗?
Do you understand?
我需要你的帮助 孩子
I need your help, son.
如果我打算有所行动
If I'm going to move on this...
就不能有哪怕一丝一毫的疑点
there can't be the least little shred of doubt.
我必须知道
I have to know...
你跟杜弗瑞恩所说的事是否属实?
if what you told Dufresne was the truth.
是的先生 千真万确!
Yes, sir. Absolutely.
那么你愿意在法官和陪审团面前...
Would you be willing to swear before a judge and jury...
手按圣经...
with your hand on the Good Book...
向万能的上帝发誓吗?
and take an oath before Almighty God himself?
只要你给我这个机会!
Just give me that chance.
那也正是我的期许!
That's what I thought.
我想你已经听说了...
I'm sure by now you've heard.
太可惜了
Terrible thing.
那么年青的一个人
A man that young...
还剩不到一年 居然想去越狱
less than a year to go, trying to escape.
哈德利被迫开枪 为此内疚不已
Broke Captain Hadley's heart to shoot him.
真的伤心透了!
Truly, it did.
我们还是忘记从前的事
We just have to put it behind us.
继续生活
Move on.
我完了!
I'm done.
一切都结束了!
Everything stops.
找其他人帮你做吧!
Get someone else to run your scams.
没有什么会结束!
Nothing stops.
不会!
Nothing.
否则叫你在这儿熬不下去
Or you will do the hardest time there is.
再也不会有看守保护你
No more protection from the guards.
我把你从单人牢房扔到鸡奸犯伙儿里
I'll pull you out of that 1 -bunk Hilton and cast you down with the sodomites.
你会知道被火车操是什么滋味
You'll think you've been fucked by a train.
图书馆?
And the library?
没了!
Gone.
用砖头一块一块封掉!
Sealed off, brick by brick.
我们在操场上把书点了 弄烧烤吃
We'll have us a little book barbecue in the yard.
几英里以外都能看得见火光
They'll see the flames for miles.
我们像土著人那样围在火边跳舞
We'll dance around it like wild Injuns.
你明白我的意思了吗? 听懂了吗?
You understand me? Catching my drift?
或许我很愚钝?
Or am I being obtuse?
再给他一个月时间考虑!
Give him another month to think about it.
我妻子曾说我是个很难理解的人
My wife used to say I'm a hard man to know.
像一本合起来的书
Like a closed book.
她总这样埋怨我
Complained about it all the time.
她很漂亮!
She was beautiful.
老天 我那么爱她!
God, I loved her.
可我不知道如何表达 仅此而已!
I didn't know how to show it, that's all.
是我害了她 瑞德!
I killed her, Red.
虽然不是我开的枪
I didn't pull the trigger...
但是我把她赶上死路的!
but I drove her away.
那就是她的死因 全是因我而起!
That's why she died, because of me...
我对她的态度!
the way I am.
那并不能把你等同于杀人凶手
That don't make you a murderer.
或许只是个不称职的丈夫
Bad husband, maybe.
你可以为此难过 但开枪的不是你!
Feel bad about it if you want, but you didn't pull the trigger.
对 不是我!
No, I didn't.
是其他人!
Somebody else did.
而我却被关在这儿舔伤口!
And I wound up in here.
运气太差 我想是
Bad luck, I guess.
霉运四处漂荡
It floats around.
总会有人碰上
It's got to land on somebody.
刚巧轮到我 而已
It was my turn, that's all.
我刚好挡了飓风的道!
I was in the path of the tornado.
只是没想到这场风暴会刮这么久!
I just didn't expect the storm would last as long as it has.
想过你有一天能出去吗?
Think you'll ever get out of here?
我?
Me?
有啊!
Yeah.
等到我头发花白 丢三拉四 骑驴找驴的那天吧!
One day, when I got a long, white beard...and two or three marbles rolling around upstairs.
我告诉你我会去哪儿
I tell you where I'd go.
芝华塔尼欧
Zihuatanejo.
哪里?
Say what?
芝华塔尼欧
Zihuatanejo.
在墨西哥
It's in Mexico.
太平洋中的一个小地方
A little place on the Pacific Ocean.
你知道墨西哥人怎么说太平洋的吗? 不知道!
You know what the Mexicans say about the Pacific?
他们说那里是没有回忆的地方
They say it has no memory.
那就是我想渡过余生的地方
That's where I want to live the rest of my life.
一个温暖的没有回忆的地方
A warm place with no memory.
开间小酒店
Open up a little hotel...
就在海滩边上
right on the beach.
买艘便宜的二手船
Buy some worthless old boat...
修葺一新
and fix it up new.
载着我的客人出海
Take my guests out...
包船钓鱼
charter fishing.
芝华塔尼欧?
Zihuatanejo?
在那儿 我需要一个能搞到东西的人
In a place like that, I could use a man that knows how to get things.
我想我适应不了外面的世界 安迪...
I don't think I could make it on the outside.
我大半辈子都关在这儿
I been in here most of my life.
我已经离不开这里了
I'm an institutional man now.
就像布鲁克斯
Just like Brooks was.
别低估自己!
You underestimate yourself.
我觉得没有!
I don't think so.
在这儿我当然能替你搞来东西 但是...
In here I'm the guy who can get things for you, sure, but...
在外面你只要有本黄页就成了
outside all you need is the Yellow Pages.
见鬼 我不想知道怎么开始的!
Hell, I wouldn't know where to begin.
太平洋?
Pacific Ocean?
靠!
Shit.
那么大的地方会吓死我的!
Scare me to death, something that big.
我不会!
Not me.
我没杀我妻子 我也没杀她的情人
I didn't shoot my wife, and I didn't shoot her lover.
不论我犯了什么错 我都已补偿过了
Whatever mistakes I made, I've paid for them and then some.
一间酒店 一条船
That hotel, that boat...
我想我要的并不过份!
I don't think that's too much to ask.
我劝你别那么想了
You shouldn't be doing this to yourself.
那只是你的狗屁白日梦!
This is just shitty pipe dreams.
墨西哥远在天边 而你近在眼前!
Mexico is way down there and you're in here...
这是现实!
and that's the way it is.
说的对 这是现实!
Yeah, right. That's the way it is.
它在天边 我在眼前!
It's down there and I'm in here.
该做个简单的选择了!
I guess it comes down to a simple choice.
要么忙着活...
Get busy living...
要么忙着死!
or get busy dying.
安迪!
Andy.
瑞德
Red.
如果你能出去的话 帮我个忙
If you ever get out of here, do me a favor.
没问题 安迪 任何事都行!
Sure, Andy. Anything.
布克斯顿附近有一大片草场 你知道布克斯顿吗?
There's a big hayfield up near Buxton. You know where Buxton is?
那儿有许多草场 有一个很特别...
- A lot of hayfields up there. - One in particular.
它有一段很长的石墙 靠北那头有棵老橡树
It's got a long rock wall with a big oak tree at the north end.
美国著名诗人
跟罗伯特·弗罗斯特诗里写的差不多
It's like something out of a Robert Frost poem.
那是我向我妻子求婚的地方
It's where I asked my wife to marry me.
我们曾在那儿野餐
We went there for a picnic...
在橡树下亲热
and made love under that oak...
我向她求婚 她答应了
and I asked and she said yes.
答应我 瑞德
Promise me, Red.
如果你能出去
If you ever get out...
找到那地方
find that spot.
在石墙根 有块在缅因州见不到的石头...
At the base of that wall, there's a rock that has no earthly business in Maine.
一块黑色的火山玻璃石
Piece of black, volcanic glass.
下面埋着我给你的东西
Something's buried under it I want you to have.
是什么 安迪?
What, Andy?
那儿埋的是什么?
What's buried under there?
这得你去挖出来...
You'll have to pry it up...
就知道了
to see.
不 我告诉你们 这小子...
No, I'm telling you. The guy is...
他说话时表情怪怪的
He's talking funny.
我真的很担心
I'm really worried about him.
那哥儿几个就上心盯着点
Let's keep an eye on him.
白天没问题 但整晚他都是一个人啊?
That's fine during the day, but at night he's all alone.
哦 我晕死
Oh, Lord.
怎么了?
What?
安迪今天到货场找过我
Andy come down to the loading dock today.
他问我要了根绳子
He asked me for a length of rope.
绳子?
Rope?
六英尺长
Six feet long.
你给他了?
And you gave it to him.
当然 我干嘛不给?
Sure. Why wouldn't I?
天啊! 海伍德!
Jesus! Heywood.
我怎么知道他要干嘛?
How was I supposed to know?
你不记得布鲁克斯了啊?
Remember Brooks Hatlen?
不 安迪不会走那条路的
Andy would never do that.
绝对不会!
Never.
我不知道
I don't know.
人的忍耐是有限度的
Every man has his breaking point.
快点 我得回家了!
Lickety-split. Want to get home.
这就好了 先生!
Just about finished, sir.
今晚有三笔要存!
Three deposits tonight.
把我的衣服送到洗衣房
Get my stuff down to the laundry.
再把我的鞋擦了
And shine my shoes.
要擦得跟镜子一样! 好的 先生
- I want them looking like mirrors. - Yes, sir.
你能回来真好 安迪
It's good having you back.
你不在的时候真是乱套了
Place wasn't the same without you.
熄灯!
Lights out!
记不清我在这里有过多少个难眠之夜
I've had some long nights in stir.
在黑暗中咀嚼孤独 只有一些心事陪着你
Alone in the dark with nothing but your thoughts...
时间被拉长得像刀锋那么细
time can draw out like a blade.
而这一夜则是我一生中最漫长的
That was the longest night of my life.
清点人数!
Give me a count!
南边三楼 到齐!
Tier 3 south, clear!
二楼245人犯未到!
Man missing on tier 2, cell 245!
杜弗瑞恩!
Dufresne!
快出来! 别跟我耍花样!
Come out. You're holding up the show!
别等我过去揪你出来 不然我打爆你的头!
Don't make me come down or I'll thump your skull for you!
你妈的折腾我 我得赶时间做事!
Damn it, you're putting me behind! I got a schedule to keep.
你最好是病了或者死了 否则我让你去吃屎!
You'd better be sick or dead in there. I shit you not!
你听到没有?
You hear me?
哦 我的上帝!
Oh, my Holy God.
查问这个监区的所有人犯
I want every man on this cellblock questioned.
- 从他的朋友开始! - 哪个? - 他!
- Start with that friend of his. - Who? - Him!
打开237号仓门!
Open 237.
你什么意思 "他就是不在这儿了?" 别跟我说这个!
What do you mean, "He just wasn't here?" Don't say that to me.
这话我不想听第二遍!
Don't tell me that again.
但是长官 他是不在了!
But sir, he wasn't.
我看到了! 海格! 你当我瞎的吗?
I can see that, Haig! Think I'm blind?
你的话是不是这意思?
Is that what you're saying?
- 我瞎了吗 海格? - 没有! 长官!
- Am I blind, Haig? - No, sir!
那么你呢? 你瞎的吗?
What about you. You blind?
- 告诉我这是什么? - 昨晚的查房记录!
- Tell me what this is. - Last night's count.
杜弗瑞恩的名字在吗? 我确定在 这儿!
You see Dufresne's name there? I sure do. Right there.
"杜弗瑞恩！"
"Dufresne."
熄灯的时候他还在牢房里
He was in his cell...at lights out.
按道理今早他也应该在牢房里
Reasonable he'd be here in the morning.
马上把他找出来!
I want him found.
不是明天 不是早饭后 就现在!
Not tomorrow, not after breakfast. Now!
遵命 长官!
Yes, sir.
跟我来 动作快点!
Let's go. Move your butts.
站好!
Stand.
说吧?
Well?
说什么?
Well, what?
我知道你们俩整天粘在一起 狼狈为奸
I see you two all the time. You're thick as thieves, you are.
他肯定对你说过什么
He must have said something.
没有 长官!
No, sir, Warden.
一个字都没有!
Not a word.
主啊 这是个神迹!
Lord, it's a miracle!
一个大活人像风中放的屁一样没了
Man vanished like a fart in the wind.
整个消失了
Nothing left...
就剩下窗台上几块破石头
but some damn rocks on a windowsill.
还有个墙上的小妞 问问她吧
And that cupcake on the wall. Let's ask her.
也许她知道
Maybe she knows.
你说什么水裤妞儿? 想谈谈吗?
What say there, fuzzy-britches? Feel like talking?
喔 当然不会!
Guess not.
她凭什么知道的多一些?
Why should she be any different?
这是一个阴谋!
This is a conspiracy.
没别的解释!
That's what this is.
一个他妈的大阴谋!
One big, damn conspiracy!
所有人都有份儿!
And everyone's in on it!
包括她!
Including her!
1966年
In 1966...
安迪·杜弗瑞恩从肖申克监狱逃脱
Andy Dufresne escaped...from Shawshank Prison.
他们追查到的只有一套泥泞的囚衣...
All they found was a muddy set of prison clothes...
一块肥皂...
a bar of soap...
还有一把很旧的鹤嘴槌
and an old rock hammer...
槌头几乎要被磨光了
damn near worn down to the nub.
我曾认为用它挖六百年才能挖穿围墙的隧道
I had thought it'd take a man 600 years to tunnel through the wall with it.
安迪只用了不到二十年就办到了
Old Andy did it in less than 20.
安迪热爱地质学
Oh, Andy loved geology.
我肯定这源自于他一丝不苟的性格
I imagine it appealed to his meticulous nature.
正如曾经的冰河时期造就了千百万年的山脉一般
An ice age here...million years of mountain building there.
地质学是关于压力和时间的研究
Geology is the study of pressure and time.
而这也正是他面临的全部问题
That's all it takes, really.
压力...
Pressure...
和时间...
and time.
当然还有一张大海报
That and a big goddamn poster.
就像我所说的
Like I said...
在监狱里 每个人都会找些事情把脑子塞满
in prison, a man will do anything to keep his mind occupied.
看来安迪最喜欢的是把他的墙壁搬运到操场上
Seems Andy's favorite hobby was toting his wall out into the exercise yard...
一次满满两把
a handful at a time.
我估计汤米被杀后
I guess after Tommy was killed...
安迪认定他在这儿已经呆够了
Andy decided he'd been here long enough.
快点 我得回家了!
Lickety-split. I want to get home.
这就好了 先生!
I'm just about finished, sir.
今晚有三笔要存!
Three deposits tonight.
安迪按照吩咐
Andy did like he was told.
把鞋擦得闪闪发亮
Buffed those shoes to a high mirror-shine.
守卫完全没有注意到
The guards simply didn't notice.
我也没有
Neither did I.
说认真的
I mean, seriously...
谁会没事干去盯别人穿什么鞋子呢?
how often do you really look at a man's shoes?
安迪爬向自由 穿过恶臭满盈的五百码
Andy crawled to freedom through 500 yards...
我简直想都不敢想那有多臭
of shit-smelling foulness I can't even imagine.
或许我只是不愿去想
Or maybe I just don't want to.
五百码
Five hundred yards.
有五个橄榄球场那么长
That's the length of five football fields.
差不多有半英里
Just shy of half a mile.
第二天早上 就在拉蔻儿的小秘密被揭穿的同时
The next morning, right about the time Raquel was spilling her secret...
一位与任何人都素昧平生的男子
a man nobody ever laid eyes on before...
来到缅因州国家银行
strolled into the Maine National Bank.
在此之前 他一直活在文件中
Until that moment, he didn't exist.
我可以帮您吗?
- Except on paper. - May I help you?
他持有所有正确的身份证明文件...
He had all the proper ID...
驾驶执照、出生证明、社保卡...
driver's license, birth certificate, Social Security card...
签名也完全吻合
And the signature was a spot-on match.
非常遗憾失去您这样一位好客户
I must say I'm sorry to be losing your business.
希望你在国外生活愉快!
I hope you'll enjoy living abroad.
谢谢!
Thank you.
我想我会的!
I'm sure I will.
先生 这是你的本票 还有什么能帮您的吗?
Here's your cashier's check, sir. Will there be anything else?
请问
Please.
能帮我把它寄出去吗?
Would you add this to your outgoing mail?
很高兴为您服务!
I'd be happy to.
- 再见! - 走好 先生!
Good day, sir.
史蒂文先生那天早上走访了波特兰地区近十二家银行
Mr. Stevens visited nearly a dozen banks in the Portland area that morning.
全部算起来
All told, he blew town...
他让典狱长诺顿的三十七万多美元灰飞烟灭
with better than $370,000 of Warden Norton's money.
十九年刑期的遣散费
Severance pay for 19 years.
早上好 波特兰号角报!
Good morning, Portland Daily Bugle.
肖申克的贪污与谋杀 检察官掌握黑钱证据 检控指日可待
主的审判将会迅速降临
《圣经》
亲爱的典狱长 你说的没错 得救之道 就在其中
出埃及记
拜伦·哈德利? 你有权保持沉默
Byron Hadley? You have the right to remain silent.
否则你所说的一切都将成为呈堂证供
If you give up this right, anything you say can be held against you in court.
我没有亲眼看到 但我听说拜伦·哈德利
I wasn't there to see, but I hear Byron Hadley sobbed like a girl...
被带走时哭得像个小女生
when they took him away.
诺顿不愿简单俯首就擒
Norton had no intention of going that quietly.
山姆·诺顿?
Samuel Norton.
我们有你的拘捕令 开门!
We have a warrant for your arrest. Open up.
把门打开!
Open the door.
我不知道是哪把钥匙
I'm not sure which key.
请你配合 诺顿!
Make it easy on yourself, Norton!
我相信最后时刻经过他大脑的
I like to think the last thing that went through his head...
除了一颗子弹
other than that bullet...
一定还有对栽在安迪手里的难以置信和迷惑不解
was to wonder how the hell Andy Dufresne ever got the best of him.
诺顿一伙倒台不久
Not long after the warden deprived us of his company...
我收到一张明信片
I got a postcard in the mail.
什么都没写 邮戳是...
It was blank, but the postmark said...
汉考克口岸 德克萨斯
Fort Hancock, Texas.
汉考克口岸
Fort Hancock...
就在边境线上
right on the border.
那是安迪出境的地方
That's where Andy crossed.
每当我脑海中浮现他驾着敞篷车一路向南的画面时
When I picture him heading south in his own car with the top down...
我总会忍不住笑出来
it always makes me laugh.
安迪·杜弗瑞恩
Andy Dufresne...
爬过了臭水沟
who crawled through a river of shit...
洗清了罪孽 在彼岸重生
and came out clean on the other side.
安迪·杜弗瑞恩
Andy Dufresne...
直奔太平洋而去
headed for the Pacific.
哈德利撕住他的领口 对吗?
Hadley's got him by the throat, right?
他说 "这鸟人想给自己来一出意外"
He says, " I believe this boy's about to have himself an accident."
我们几个跟他最熟的时常聊起他
Those of us who knew him best talk about him often.
我发誓 他有种神奇的魅力
I swear, the stuff he pulled...
"我的朋友能有几瓶啤酒"
"My friends could use a couple of beers."
他办到了!
And he got it!
有时我会伤感 因为安迪已经不在了
Sometimes it makes me sad, though...Andy being gone.
我只能提醒自己有些鸟是不能关在笼子里的
I have to remind myself that some birds aren't meant to be caged.
它们的羽翼是如此绚丽 光芒夺目
Their feathers are just too bright.
当它们飞出牢笼时
And when they fly away...
会让那些觉得把它们关起来是种罪恶的人感到由衷的喜悦
the part of you that knows it was a sin to lock them up does rejoice.
但同时 它们的离开让你生活的地方空荡荡的
But still...the place you live in is that much more drab and empty that they're gone.
可能我只是过于想念我的朋友了
I guess I just miss my friend.
请坐!
Please sit down.
艾力斯·博伊德·瑞丁（瑞德的全名）
Ellis Boyd Redding...
你因终身监禁已被关了40年了
your files say you've served 40 years of a life sentence.
你觉得你改过自新了吗?
You feel you've been rehabilitated?
改过自新?
Rehabilitated?
哦 让我想想看
Well, now, let me see.
我不明白那是什么意思
I don't have any idea what that means.
意思是你已经准备好重返社会...
It means you're ready to rejoin society...
我知道你是怎么想的 老弟
I know what you think it means, sonny.
对我来说那只是一个构词法的产物
To me it's just a made-up word.
给政客们用的词汇
A politician's word so that...
让你这样的年轻人能穿西装打领带
young fellas like yourself can wear a suit and a tie...
有事可做
and have a job.
你倒底想知道些什么?
What do you really want to know?
我对自己的罪行感到后悔吗?
Am I sorry for what I did?
那么 你后悔吗?
Well, are you?
没有一天我不感到后悔的
There's not a day goes by I don't feel regret.
不是因为我被关在这儿 或者为了迎合你的想法
Not because I'm in here or because you think I should.
我回首往事
I look back on the way I was then...
一个年轻的...愚蠢的孩子铸成大错
a young...stupid kid who committed that terrible crime.
我想和他谈谈
I want to talk to him.
想和他讲讲人生大义
I want to try and talk some sense to him.
教教他为人处世之道
Tell him the way things are.
但我做不到
But I can't.
那孩子早都不在了
That kid's long gone...
只剩下你面前这个老头子
and this old man is all that's left.
我得跟他继续生活
I got to live with that.
改过自新?
Rehabilitated?
只是个狗屁字眼
It's just a bullshit word.
请你继续 在表格上盖章吧 老弟 别浪费我的时间了
So you go on and stamp your forms, sonny, and stop wasting my time.
说句实话
Because to tell you the truth...
我根本不在乎!
I don't give a shit.
批准
你的 小姐
Here you go, miss.
可以去趟洗手间吗?
Restroom break?
你不用每次要小便都来问我 只管去就是了!
You don't need to ask me every time you need to go take a piss. Just go.
四十年来我连小便都需要被批准
Forty years I've been asking permission to piss.
不申请的话一滴都挤不出来
I can't squeeze a drop without say-so.
现实是很难面对的
There's a harsh truth to face.
我没办法习惯外面的生活
No way I'm going to make it on the outside.
我总在想怎样才能违反假释条例
All I do anymore is think of ways to break my parole...
那样他们会把我送回去
so maybe they'd send me back.
生活在恐惧中是很可怕的事
Terrible thing, to live in fear.
布鲁克斯知道
Brooks Hatlen knew it.
他知道得太清楚了
Knew it all too well.
我只想回到适合我的地方
All I want is to be back where things make sense.
不用惶惶不可终日的地方
Where I won't have to be afraid all the time.
只是有一件事阻止了我
Only one thing stops me.
我答应安迪的事
A promise I made to Andy.
到了!
There it is.
非常感谢 先生!
Much obliged, sir.
亲爱的瑞德
Dear Red:
若你能看到这封信 那你已经出来了
If you're reading this, you've gotten out...
既然你已经跑了这么远 不妨再跑远一点
and if you've come this far, maybe you'd come a bit further.
你还记得那个地方的名字 是吗?
You remember the name of the town, don't you?
芝华塔尼欧!
Zihuatanejo!
我需要一个能干的人和我一起完成我的计划
I could use a good man to help me get my project on wheels.
我期待你的到来 棋盘已经准备好了
I'll keep an eye out for you, and the chessboard ready.
记住 瑞德
Remember, Red...
希望是个好东西
hope is a good thing...
也许是世间最好的东西
maybe the best of things.
好东西从不会逝去
And no good thing ever dies.
我希望这封信能等到你
I will be hoping that this letter finds you...
并能看到你安然无恙
and finds you well.
你的朋友
Your friend...
安迪
Andy.
"要么忙着活
"Get busy living...
要么忙着死"
or get busy dying. "
这话太他妈的对了
That's goddamn right.
瑞德也住过
这是有生以来第二次...
For the second time in my life...
我有做贼心虚的感觉
I'm guilty of committing a crime.
我担心他们会设下路障 当然 这是因为有人违反假释条例
Parole violation. Of course I doubt they'll toss up any roadblocks for that.
而不是为了我这种老家伙
Not for an old crook like me.
德克萨斯州 汉考克口岸 谢谢!
Fort Hancock, Texas, please.
我发现我很兴奋 如坐针毡 思绪纷乱
I find I'm so excited I can barely sit still or hold a thought in my head.
我想这是一个自由人才能感受到的兴奋
I think it's the excitement only a free man can feel.
一个自由人开始了漫长的旅程
A free man at the start of a long journey...
伴随着未知的结局
whose conclusion is uncertain.
我希望我能越过边界 完成这段旅程
I hope I can make it across the border.
我希望见到我的朋友 紧握他的手
I hope to see my friend and shake his hand.
我希望太平洋的海水和我梦中一样蓝
I hope the Pacific is as blue as it has been in my dreams.
我希望...
I hope.
导演的经纪人和朋友 本片完成前因艾滋病去世
谨此此片纪念 亚伦·格林